<!-- -*- DocBook -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V3.1//EN" "../docbkx412/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>CCProbe Software Reference</title> 
    <author><firstname>Stephen</firstname><surname>Bannasch</surname></author> 

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/gs-7-1.png" format="PNG" scale="50"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <date> 9 Jan 2002</date>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year>
      <holder>Concord Consortium</holder>
    </copyright>
<legalnotice>
<para>
This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation 
under the following Grant Numbers:
</para>
  <para>TEEMSS: ESI-9986419</para>
  <para>Data and Models: REC-9973179</para>
  <para>Exploratorium: ESI-9901985</para>
  <para>MAC: REC-0115699</para>
<para>
Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in 
this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect 
the views of the National Science Foundation.
</para>
</legalnotice>
</bookinfo>

  <chapter><title>Introduction to CCProbe</title> 
    <para>CC has developed an
    open-source application called CCProbe that is scriptable,
    configurable, and supports probe-based visualization, analysis,
    and calibration components.  CCProbe also includes components for
    folders, text, drawings, and images, which can be integrated with
    the probeware to create curricular activities and a lab book
    portfolio in which work can be saved and shared.
    </para>
    <para>
    CCProbe and the CCLabBook system are written in Waba (an open
    source variant of Java) and run on a wide range of operating
    systems including PalmOS, WinCE, PocketPC, Windows, MacOS Classic,
    MacOS X, Linux and other Unix operating systems. This means that
    not only does our software runs on almost any computer made in the
    last five years. As new computers and operating systems are
    created, the software will quickly run on those, as well.
</para>
<figure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/ccprobe-screenshot1.png" format="PNG" scale="50"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>Screenshot of CCProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>
    <para>
For more information visit the 
<ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware">
CCprobeware web site.
</ulink>
</para>
<para> The CCProbe Software is Copyright (c) 2001, 2002 by
Concord Consortium, All Rights Reserved, The software and the source
code is free to use and copy under the 
<ulink url="http://gnu.org/licenses.html">GNU General Public license</ulink>.
</para>


    <section><title>CCProbe CCA2D2 v2 Interface</title>
      <para>

CCProbe works with the either the new CCProbe Interface (CCA2D2 v2)
and probes developed for the TEEMSS project or the older
CCA2D2 v1 interface developed for the Data and Models project.
</para>

      <para> The interface is the device that goes between the
computer and probes. Our latest design, called the CCProbeInterface,
is built using the latest low-power, low-cost, precision electronic
components with a design that reduces the cost of probes that are used
with it.  The interface has batteries to allow use of power-hungry
probes as well as portable unattended datalogging operation.  However
if the batteries are dead or missing the CCProbe Interface can still
communicate with the CCProbe software and inform the user.  </para>

      <para>
<figure><title>A schematic block diagram of the CCProbe Interface.</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata
fileref="images/png/ccprobe-interface-blockdiag.png" format="PNG" scale="25"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata
fileref="images/eps/ccprobe-interface-blockdiag.eps" format="EPS" scale="25"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>A schematic block diagram of the CCProbe Interface.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>
</para>

      <para> The CCProbeInterface contains two kinds of voltage
sensors. One is fast and moderately sensitive, while the other is
extremely sensitive but slow. The fast one can sense up to four inputs
to within five millivolts as fast as ten thousand times per
second. This is good for detecting sound, the forces in a collision,
or the flash from a bulb as it burns out.  </para>

      <para> The slow voltage sensor can detect four inputs to within
a couple of microvolts about three times a second. This high
sensitivity is valuable because we can dispense with the cost of
electronics often used in input circuits. For instance, we can make a
sensitive temperature sensor from two wires of different metals, a
so-called thermocouple. The junction of a typical thermocouple
generates a few tens of microvolts for every degree temperature
change. This means that two wires can be made into a very sensitive
thermometer, a sensor anyone can build.  </para>

      <para>
We made the first version of our interface hardware, the CCA2D2 v1
interface in the Spring of 2001 for the Data and Models project. The
CCA2D2 v1 interface capabilities include a 2-channel, 3 Hz, 24 bit
ADC, as well as a 2-channel, 200 Hz, 10-bit ADC and additional digital
I/O.
      </para>
      <para>
During the summer of 2001 we expanded the capabilities by developing
the CCA2D2 v2 interface interface for the TEEMSS project to support
two probe ports with automatically identified probes along with
batteries to supply power to higher current probes and support
operation while not connected to a computer. Currently the CCProbe
software works with the CCA2D2 v2 interface, however the software
architecture is being built to support collection of data from many
different interfaces.

      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>CCProbes</title>
      <para>
      As illustrated below we have developed some very exciting
      new probes.  Each of these probes has a memory chip which holds
      identifying and calibration information about the probe.
</para>

      <para>
The CCSmartWheel. The ultrasonic motion detector developed by project
staff 16 years ago is inherently expensive and a bit difficult for
beginners to use. We have developed an alternative that uses an
optical encoder on a CDROM wheel. This wheel can be easily attached to
a cart, meter stick, or pulley, making it quite versatile.
</para>
<figure><title>CCSmartWheel</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/smartwheel.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/tiff/smartwheel.tiff" format="TIFF"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCSmartWheel</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

      <para>
The CCForceProbe. We dusted off the old idea of using a Hall effect
sensor next to a magnet on a metal beam, all quite inexpensive. When the
sensor is midway between the poles of the magnet and one-half pole
separation away, it's response is linear in displacement parallel to the
probes. Since the displacement of the arm holding the magnet is
proportional to force, this makes a very sensitive probe.
</para>
<figure><title>CCForceProbe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/forceprobe.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/tiff/forceprobe.tiff" format="TIFF"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCForceProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

      <para>
The CCTemperatureProbe, uses the tiny tip of a thermocouple to measure
temperature. There are many fascinating thermal experiments possible
which are impractical to consider using a normal temperature
probe. This sensor responds so quickly to changes in air temperature
that the vertical temperature profile in a room can be determined in
one 30 second experiment.
</para>
<figure><title>CCTemperatureProbe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/tempprobe.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/tiff/tempprobe.tiff" format="TIFF"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCTemperatureProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

      <para>
The CCVoltageCurrentProbe, can be used to measure voltage or current.
Further processing of these values in the CCProbe application allows
the recording of electrical power and energy.
</para>
<figure><title>CCVoltageCurrentProbe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/voltagecurrentprobe.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/tiff/voltagecurrentprobe.tiff" format="TIFF"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCVoltageCurrentProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

      <para>
The CCLightProbe is used to measure visible light in either an indoor
or outdoor illumination range.
      </para>
<figure><title>CCLightProbe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/lightprobe.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/tiff/lightprobe.tiff" format="TIFF"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCLightProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>
    </section>
    <section><title>LabBook</title>
      <para>
Learning requires more than a good tool. Students need to be guided,
challenged to predict, and encouraged to reflect. CCProbe uses the
organizing principle of a lab notebook which contains both curricular
activities and a portfolio of student work.  While CCProbe includes
many traditional probeware tools such as real-time graphing, analysis,
calibration, and saved datasets it also includes software objects for
taking notes, drawing sketches, answering questions, and displaying
images.  CCProbe also supports folders and compound objects similar
to web pages in which the basic objects can be combined together into
activities.
</para>

      <para> We call this functionality that CCProbe is built upon the
CCLabBook System.  All the activities and student work are saved in
one place.  Right now we create activities using a structured
XML-based editing system from which CCLabBook objects, html web pages,
and printed pdf versions of the activities are automatically
generated. In the future, teachers will be able to easily modify the
activities or create their own using a web-based authoring
system. Once generated, an activity can be distributed to all
students.  An individual CCLabBook can be easily moved between
handheld and full-size computer systems allowing students to
investigate, edit, and organize information anywhere.  </para>

      <para>
After a class of students has completed an activity the work collected
in individual CCLabBooks is combined on the teachers computer where it
can be browsed, commented on, and archived.  Additionally, the teacher
can place new activities in the student CCLabBooks.
</para>

      <para>
An essential design goal of the CCLabBook System is to support
transparent communication of portfolio objects between all these
systems. For example after using CCProbe on a Palm computer to collect
temperature and light data in the field, the LabBook on the Palm can
be saved onto a server where it is accessible from other locations
such as computers in the computer lab.

      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>DataCollectors</title>
      <para>
      CCProbe initially comes with five different types of
      DataCollectors: Temperature, Force, SmartWheel, VoltageCurrent,
      and Light.  These are the objects in the LabBook which combine
      collection and display of of real-time data from the probes.  In
      addition to real-time graphing DataCollectors support annotation
      of points on the graph, display of annotated points as a bar
      graph, flexible axis scaling and translation, and note taking.
      After collecting data the data can be saved as a DataSet for
      later display or analysis.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>DataSets</title>
      <para>
      DataSets are LabBook objects that hold saved collections of data
      from a DataCollector.  A DataSet will save the data from a
      collection until the DataSet object is deleted.  All the graph
      display and annotation tools available in a DataCollector are
      also available in a DataSet.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Drawings</title>
      <para>
      Freehand drawings and sketches can be created in a LabBook
      Drawing object.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Notes</title>
      <para>
      A LabBook Notes object holds writing.  At this point when you are
writing into a note you must type the Return character at the end
of every line.  The Note object will not automatically wrap entered
text onto the next line.  
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Unit Convertors</title>
      <para>
      In order to more easily do calculations with different units we
      have a Unit Comnvertor calculator.  This allows conversions from
and to many different physical quantities.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Images</title>
      <para>
      On desktop systems images can be loaded into LabBook Image
      objects.  After loading into the LabBook the images can be
      displayed on any system that CCProbe runs on.  On the Palm IIIc
which only has 256 colors we use the Netscape 216 web color pallete
for displayed images.  CCProbe can import ".bmp" images and if it is
running on a Macintosh it can import a wide variety of images using
QuickTime.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Supernotes</title>
      <para>
      CCProbe supports a compund document object we call a Supernote.
      A Supernote is similar to an html document and can hold text,
      links to other objects and even the objects themselves embedded
      directly in a Supernote.  Supernote creation and editing can be
done on a dektop system.  Advanced Supernote creation can more easily
be done by writing the object structure in XML and creating the
LabBook with the XML2LabBook conversion tool.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>License</title>
      <para>
      CCProbe is free software that can be downloaded, copied, and
      used as you wish. While we retain copyright for all the source
      code we have written we specifically provide you with this
software with the GNU General Public License
      which allows you access to and the right to modify the
      source code for CCProbe.  However the GPL license states that if
      you distribute the changes in the source code you must also
      apply the same license to your copyrighted code.
      </para>
      <para>
      Our goal is to create a community of users, researchers and
      developers who can contribute towards making CCProbe a more
      useful tool.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Source Code</title>
      <para>
CCProbe is written in Waba an open source Java-like language for handhelds.
Waba is its own programming platform including a language, virtual
machine, class file format and set of base classes.
</para>
<para>
Because of the way Waba was designed, developers can use Java
development tools to write Waba programs and Waba programs can run as
Java applets or applications with no native code.
</para>
<para>
Waba applications can run under Java but, for the most part, Java
programs that use the Java Class Libraries can't run under Waba.
</para>
<para>>
      You can get a copy of of the source code and license by
      following the appropriate links at the 
<ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware">CCProbeware web site.</ulink>
</para>
</section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>Installing CCProbe</title>
    <para>
    CCProbe is written in Waba, an open-source GPL licensed subset of
    Java specifically designed to work on handheld computers. Normally
    when it is run on a Palm or Windows CE system the CCProbe Waba
application
    is executed by the Waba virtual machine similar to how Java
    programs are often run. This is the method used on the PocketPC
    version of CCProbe. However on the Palm we use Jump and
WabaJump to
    compile the Waba application into PalmOS 68000 machine code in
    order to operate as fast as possible.
    </para>

<para> You can download Packages that contain CCProbe, a LabBook,
documentation, and any OS specific programs needed to run CCProbe by
browsing here: <ulink
url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/ccprobe-downloads.html">CCProbe
Download Page</ulink>.</para>
    <para>
On MacOS, Windows, and Unix/Linux systems the CCProbe runs as a Java
application using the Waba for Java classes that implement the Waba
API on top of Java. On Unix/Linux systems Waba applications can run
using the Java VM from Sun.
    </para>

<table frame='all'><title>Available Packages of CCProbe</title>
<tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
<colspec colname='c1'/>
<colspec colname='c2'/>
<colspec colname='c3'/>
<thead>
  <row>
    <entry>Operating System</entry>
    <entry>archive type</entry>
    <entry>link</entry>
  </row>
</thead>
<tbody>
  <row>
    <entry>PalmOS</entry>
    <entry>exe for Windows</entry>
    <entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-palmos/CCProbe.exe">CCProbe.exe</ulink></entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>PalmOS</entry>
    <entry>tarred and gzipped for Unix</entry>
    <entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-palmos/CCProbe.tgz">CCProbe.tgz</ulink></entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>PalmOS</entry>
    <entry>binhex self-extracting archive for MacOS</entry>
    <entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-palmos/CCProbe.sea.hqx">CCProbe.sea.hqx</ulink></entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>PocketPC (for MIPS and StrongArm)</entry>
    <entry>exe for Windows</entry>
    <entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-pocketpc/CCProbe.exe">CCProbe.exe</ulink></entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>MacOS Classic</entry>
    <entry>binhex self-extracting archive for MacOS</entry>
    <entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-macos-classic/CCProbe.sea.hqx">CCProbe.sea.hqx</ulink></entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>MacOS X</entry>
    <entry>binhex self-extracting archive for MacOS</entry>
    <entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-macosx/CCProbe.sea.hqx">CCProbe.sea.hqx</ulink></entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>Windows</entry>
    <entry>exe for Windows</entry>
    <entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-windows/CCProbe.exe">CCProbe.exe</ulink></entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>Linux/Unix</entry>
    <entry>tarred and gzipped for Unix</entry>
    <entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-unix/CCProbe.tgz">CCProbe.tgz</ulink></entry>
  </row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

    <section><title>MacOS Classic</title>
      <para>
      Installing and running CCProbe on MacOS Classic
      </para>

      <para>
CCProbe requires Apple's MacOS Runtime for Java (MRJ). MRJ implements
Sun's Java 1.1 standard. The most recent version of MRJ is version
2.2.5. Don't be confused by Apple's numbering of their Java virtual
machine. It does not relate to Sun's numbering system for Java. You
can get the latest version of MRJ here:
    </para>
      <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.info.apple.com/support/downloads.html"> http://www.info.apple.com/support/downloads.html
    </ulink>
      </para>
<para>
Once you are there do a search for "mrj".
</para>
      <para>
After installing MRJ you can start the application CCProbe by
double-clicking it.
    </para>
      <para>
Changing the CCProbe application window size
    </para>
      <para>
Load the file CCProbe.properties into an program which can edit a text
file such as Eudora, BBEdit, or Simpletext
    </para>
      <para>
Look for the following line:
    </para>
      <para>
com.apple.mrj.application.parameters=/color /w 600 /h 400 CCProbe
    </para>
      <para>
The numbers after the /w and /h set the width and the height of the
application window.
    </para>

      <para>
Edit these numbers and save the file. The next time the CCProbe
application is run it will use the new specification as the window
size.
    </para>

      <para>
Using CCProbe with a Mac that has a USB port
    </para>

      <para> In order to use the CCProbe Interface you will need a
USB-to-Serial Adapter. We have used Keyspan's USA-19 and USA-19W, and
USA-19QW.  In addition you will need a DB9 cable assembly for the
CCProbe Interface.  This consists of a short length of 6-conductor
modular telephone cable, an RJ-11 to DB9 adaptor, and a numll-modem
cable.
    </para>

      <para>
You must install the latest drivers from Keyspan. You can download
them here:
    </para>

      <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.keyspan.com/downloads/">
      http://www.keyspan.com/downloads/
    </ulink>
      </para>

<para>
Setting the location of the Serial Communications Port
</para>
<para>
The first time CCProbe attempts to connect to the CCProbe interface
through the serial port it will ask which serial port to use to
connect to the interface.
</para>
<para>
If you use an older Macintosh with a serial port you will most likely
select either the Printer/Modem port or if you have two serial ports
select the Printer port.  If you have troubles connecting make sure
that Appletalk is not already trying to use the serial port by opening
the Appletalk control panel.  If AppleTalk is using a serial port then
you can turn appletalk off with a small control at the bottom of the
Chooser window.
</para>

</section>


    <section><title>MacOS X</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Windows</title>
      <para>
      Installing and running CCProbe on Windows
      </para>
      
      <para>
CCProbe requires Sun's Java 1.1 or higher. You can get the latest
version of the Java 2 Runtime Environment, Standard Edition for
Windows here:
    </para>

      <para>
      <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.3/jre/download-windows.html">
      http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.3/jre/download-windows.html
      </ulink>
      </para>

      <para>
Even though it is called Java 2, Sun's internal numbering calls this
Java version 1.3.1.
    </para>

      <para>
In addition the Java Communications API must be installed to support
serial communications with the interface.
    </para>

      <para>
1. Install the Java Communications API
    </para>

      <para>
In order to install the following components you must determine where
the java home directory is on your system. On my Windows 2000 system
it is C:\Program Files\JavaSoft\1.3.1. In the procedure below replace
occurances of javahome with the location of the java home directory on
your system.
    </para>

      <para>
The home page for the Java Communications API is:
    </para>

      <para>
      <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/javacomm/">
      http://java.sun.com/products/javacomm/
      </ulink>
      </para>

      <para>
Download Version 2.0 for Microsoft Windows.
    </para>

      <para>
The Java Communications API will be saved on your computer in a ZIP
archive. You will need a utility to expand the archive. The free
program FreeZip works well. You can get it here:
    </para>

      <para>
      <ulink url="http://crnet.tucows.com/system/preview/194266.html">
      http://crnet.tucows.com/system/preview/194266.html
      </ulink>
      </para>

      <para>
Most of the items are not needed however copy the three items below:
    </para>

      <para>
a. Copy win32com.dll to the javahome\bin directory
    </para>

      <para>
b. Copy comm.jar to the javahome\lib\ext
    </para>

      <para>
c. Place javax.comm.properties in the javahome\lib
    </para>

      <para>
2. Install CCProbe
    </para>


      <para>
a. Create folder CCProbe anywhere you like
    </para>

      <para>
b. Copy CCProbe.jar and CCProbe.bat to the CCProbe folder
    </para>

      <para>
you are ready to go
    </para>

      <para>
to start: double-click on CCProbe.bat
    </para>

      <para>
Specifying the location of the Serial Communications Port
    </para>

      <para>
Changing the CCProbe application window size
    </para>

      <para>
Load the file CCProbe.bat into an program which can edit a text file
such as WordPad
    </para>

      <para>
Edit the first line in the file:
    </para>

      <para>
java -cp CCProbe.jar waba.applet.Applet /w 600 /h 400 /color CCProbe
    </para>

      <para>
The numbers after the /w and /h set the width and the height of the
application window.  Edit these numbers and save the file. The next
time the CCProbe application is run it will use the new specification
as the window size.
      </para>

    </section>
    <section><title>Unix/Linux</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>PocketPC</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>PalmOS</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Specifying the location of the serial port</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Updating your version of CCProbe</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>Using the CCProbe LabBook</title> <section><title>LabBook Views</title>
      <para>
      </para>
      <section><title>Tree</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Page</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section><title>LabBook Objects</title>
      <para>
      </para>
      <section><title>Folders</title>
	<para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Notes</title>
	<para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>DataCollectors</title>
	<para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>DataSets</title>
	<para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Drawings</title>
	<para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>UnitConvertors</title>
	<para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Images</title>
	<para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>SuperNotes</title>
	<para>
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section><title>File Menu</title>
      <para>
      </para>
      <section><title>New..</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Open..</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Renaming</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Exporting</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Importing</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Deleting</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>About CCProbe</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Exit</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section><title> Edit Menu</title>
      <para>
      </para>
      <section><title>Cut</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Paste</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Properties</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Toggle Hidden </title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter><title>Using CCProbe DataCollectors</title>
    <para>
    </para>
    <section><title>Graphing data with CCProbe</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Saving Data in a DataSet</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Exporting Data</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Multiple Data Collections</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Clearing the Data</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Marking and Labeling the Graph</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Saving Notes With the DataSet</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Viewing as a Bar Graph</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Changing the Axes and Moving the graph</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Selecting an area and Zooming In</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>DataCollector Properties Dialog</title>
      <para>
      </para>
      <section><title>Y Axis Properties</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>X Axis Properties</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Graph Properties</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Probe Properties</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Calibration Dialog</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section><title>Types of DataCollectors</title>
      <para>
      </para>
      <section><title>Temperature</title>
        <para>
	</para>
        <section><title>Connecting the Temperature Probe</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Output Mode: C, F, K</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Calibration</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section><title>Light</title>
        <para>
	</para>
        <section><title>Connecting the Light Probe</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Output Mode</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Calibration</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section><title>SmartWheel</title>
        <para>
	</para>
        <section><title>Connecting the SmartWheel Probe</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Port Selection: A</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Output Mode</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Calibration</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section><title>Force</title>
        <para>
	</para>
        <section><title>Connecting the Force Probe</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Output Mode</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Calibration</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section><title>Voltage/Current</title>
        <para>
	</para>
        <section><title>Connecting the Voltage/Current Probe</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Output Mode</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Calibration</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section><title>RawData</title>
        <para>
	</para>
        <section><title>Using the RawData DataCollector</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Output Mode</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
        <section><title>Calibration</title>
	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section><title>File Menu</title>
      <para>
      </para>
      <section><title>Beam</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Save Data</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Export Data</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>About CCProbe</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Exit</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section><title>Edit</title>
      <para>
      </para>
      <section><title>Properties</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
      <section><title>Save Profile</title>
        <para>
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter><title>Using CCProbe DataSets</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>Using CCProbe Drawings</title>
    <para>
    </para>
    <section><title>Drawing</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Erasing</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Clearing the Whole Picture</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Setting the Pen Color</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>Using CCProbe Unit Convertors</title>
    <para>
    </para>
    <section><title>Length</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Mass</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Time</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Temperature</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Area</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Volume</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Energy</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Force</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Power</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Pressure</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Electricity</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>Using CCProbe Images</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>Using CCProbe Supernotes</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>LabBook Management</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>Advanced Features</title>
    <para>
    </para>
    <section><title>Folder Modes</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Editing Supernotes</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>Reporting Bugs and Feature Requests</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter><title>CCProbe Development</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </chapter>
</book>
