<!-- -*- DocBook -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1.2//EN" "../docbkx412/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>CCProbe Software Reference</title> 
    <author><firstname>Stephen</firstname><surname>Bannasch</surname></author> 
    <date> 21 February 2002</date>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year>
      <holder>Concord Consortium</holder>
    </copyright>
    <corpname>Concord Consortium</corpname>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/jpg/gs-7-1.jpg" format="JPG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>incomplete version, released: $Date$, 
$Revision$
      </para>
      <para>
This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation 
under the following Grant Numbers:
      </para>
      <para>TEEMSS: ESI-9986419</para>
      <para>Data and Models: REC-9973179</para>
      <para>Exploratorium: ESI-9901985</para>
      <para>MAC: REC-0115699</para>
      <para>
Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in 
this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect 
the views of the National Science Foundation.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter><title>Introduction</title> 
    
<para> CCProbe is an open-source application developed at the Concord
Consortium that is scriptable, configurable, and supports probe-based
visualization, analysis, and calibration components. CCProbe also
includes components for folders, text, drawings, and images, which can
be integrated with the probeware to create curricular activities and a
lab book portfolio in which work can be saved and shared.  CCProbe has
been specifically designed to run well on handheld computers such as
those running PalmOS or Microsoft PocketPC. Written in Waba, an open
source subset of Java specifically designed for Handheld computers
CCProbe is licensed under the GPL and it runs on PalmOS, WinCE,
PocketPC, Windows, MacOS, and Unix.</para>

<para> CCProbe is the first program written using the CC LabBook
architecture.  The CC LabBook system is the underlying software
architecture that supports a multi-platform object-oriented portfolio.
This portfolio can contain curricular activities, student work and
assessments.</para>

<para> CCProbe and the CCLabBook system are written in Waba, an open
source Java-like language for handhelds which runs on a wide range of
operating systems including PalmOS, WinCE, PocketPC, Windows, MacOS
Classic, MacOS X, Linux and other Unix operating systems. This means
that not only does our software runs on almost any computer made in
the last five years. As new computers and operating systems are
created, the software will quickly run on those, as well.  </para>

<para>The current projects at the Concord Consortium contributing to
the development of CCProbe are:</para>

<informaltable frame='none'>
<tgroup cols='1'>
<colspec colwidth='6.0in'/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Technology Enhanced Elementary and Middle School Science (TEEMSS)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Data and Models </entry></row>
<row><entry>Electronic Guidebook (Exploratorium) </entry></row>
<row><entry>Modeling across the Curriculum (MAC)</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

<para> The Concord Consortium is a tax-exempt non-profit education
research and development organization. The appearance of new, emerging
technologies has the potential to ignite explosive strides in learning
capacity and curriculum development. Harnessing these technological
resources can result in a powerful extension of educational resources
to all people, regardless of their circumstances. The Concord
Consortium is committed to leading this drive forward by developing
and using the best in educational technology.  </para>

<figure>
    <title>Screenshot of CCProbe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/ccprobe-screenshot1.png" format="PNG" depth="200"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>Screenshot of CCProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para> For more information visit the <ulink
url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware"> CCprobeware web site.  </ulink>
</para>

<para> The CCProbe Software is Copyright (c) 2001, 2002 by Concord
Consortium, All Rights Reserved, The software and the source code is
free to use and copy under the <ulink
url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/licenses.html">GNU General Public
license</ulink>.  </para>


<section><title>CCProbe CCA2D2 v2 Interface</title>

<para>CCProbe works with the either the new CCProbe Interface (CCA2D2 v2)
and probes developed for the TEEMSS project or the older
CCA2D2 v1 interface developed for the Data and Models project.
</para>

<para> The interface is the device that goes between the computer and
probes. Our latest design, called the CCProbeInterface, is built using
the latest low-power, low-cost, precision electronic components with a
design that reduces the cost of probes that are used with it.  See
<xref linkend="ccprobe-interface"/> below. The interface has batteries
to allow use of power-hungry probes as well as portable unattended
datalogging operation.  However if the batteries are dead or missing
the CCProbe Interface can still communicate with the CCProbe software
and inform the user.  </para>

<figure id="ccprobe-interface"><title>A schematic block diagram of the CCProbe Interface.</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata
fileref="images/png/ccprobe-interface-blockdiag.png" format="PNG" depth="240"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>The CCProbeInterface is an analog and digital interface with
both real-time and datalogging capabilities. It has two ports for
probes, a serial interface for connecting to handheld, laptop, and
desktop computer systems and a IrDA port. The microcontroller and the
low-power I/O functions are operated with a 3.3V bus which can be
powered directly from either the handshake line on a connected serial
port, from 2 internal AA batteries, or from a wall blob. The batteries
through the power convertor can supply up to 300 mA at 5V to systems
that need more power than can be stolen from the serial port such as
high-power probes and the IrDA communications port.</para>

<para> The CCProbeInterface contains two kinds of voltage sensors. One
is fast and moderately sensitive, while the other is extremely
sensitive but slow. The fast one can sense up to four inputs to within
five millivolts as fast as ten thousand times per second. This is good
for detecting sound, the forces in a collision, or the flash from a
bulb as it burns out.  </para>

<para> The slow voltage sensor can detect four inputs to within
a couple of microvolts about three times a second. This high
sensitivity is valuable because we can dispense with the cost of
electronics often used in input circuits. For instance, we can make a
sensitive temperature sensor from two wires of different metals, a
so-called thermocouple. The junction of a typical thermocouple
generates a few tens of microvolts for every degree temperature
change. This means that two wires can be made into a very sensitive
thermometer, a sensor anyone can build.  </para>

</section>

<section><title>CCProbes</title>

<para>As illustrated below we have developed some very exciting
new probes for the Teemss Project.  Each of these probes has a memory
chip which holds identifying and calibration information about the
probe.  </para>

     <section> <title>CCSmartWheel</title>
<para>
The CCSmartWheel. The ultrasonic motion detector developed by project
staff 16 years ago is inherently expensive and a bit difficult for
beginners to use. We have developed an alternative that uses an
optical encoder on a CDROM wheel. This wheel can be easily attached to
a cart, meter stick, or pulley, making it quite versatile.</para>

<para>The CCSmartWheel is used for measuring velocity and with
additional processing produces position and acceleration data. In
addition it can be used to measure angular rotation such as that
produced by a pendulum. It uses a cdrom with a simple bearing on the
hub and an extended shaft to either hold or attach to a moving
object. We measure the rotation using optical quadrature
methods.</para>


<figure><title>CCSmartWheel</title>
    <mediaobject>

<!--
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/tiff/smartwheel.tiff" format="TIFF"/>
      </imageobject>
-->

      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/smartwheel.png" format="PNG" depth="240"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCSmartWheel</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>
    </section>
     <section> <title>CCForceProbe</title>

<para>The CCForceProbe. We dusted off the old idea of using a Hall
effect sensor next to a magnet on a metal beam, all quite
inexpensive. When the sensor is midway between the poles of the magnet
and one-half pole separation away, it's response is linear in
displacement parallel to the probes. Since the displacement of the arm
holding the magnet is proportional to force, this makes a very
sensitive probe.  </para> 

<para>The CCForceProbe has two force ranges: +/- 20 and 200
Newtons. The smaller screw eye measures forces in the range of -20 to
+20 Newtons. Forces from -200 to +200 Newtons can be measured at the
larger eyebolt.</para>

<figure><title>CCForceProbe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/forceprobe.png" format="PNG" depth="240"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCForceProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>
</section>

<section> <title>CCTemperatureProbe</title>

<para>
The CCTemperatureProbe, uses the tiny tip of a thermocouple to measure
temperature. There are many fascinating thermal experiments possible
which are impractical to consider using a normal temperature
probe. This sensor responds so quickly to changes in air temperature
that the vertical temperature profile in a room can be determined in
one 30 second experiment.</para>

<para>The TEEMSS Fast Response Temperature Probe is based on an
earlier design done for the Data and Models project at CC. The active
sensor is a Type E thermocouple made of wire 0.010" in diameter. The
two ends of the thermocouple wire are soldered together to create a
very low thermal mass temperature probe. The sensor will return to 90%
of equilibrium after 30s in still air. The range is -50 to 110 degrees
C with a resolution of 0.1 degrees. The cold junction of the
thermocouple is compensated with an analog output IC temperature
sensor.</para>


<figure><title>CCTemperatureProbe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/tempprobe.png" format="PNG" depth="240"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCTemperatureProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>
</section>

<section> <title>CCVoltageCurrentProbe</title>

<para>The TEEMSS Voltage and Current Probe can measure voltage and
current simultaneously. The product of these measurements is Power in
Watts and the integration of Power over time is Energy in Joules. The
probe measures +/- 20 volts and +/- 2 amps. The different values are
reported by the probe simultaneously to both the fast 10-bit and slow
24-bit input channels of the probe port.</para>


<figure><title>CCVoltageCurrentProbe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/voltagecurrentprobe.png"
format="PNG" depth="240"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCVoltageCurrentProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>
</section>

<section> <title>CCLightProbe</title>

<para>The CCLightProbe is used to measure visible light in either an
indoor or outdoor illumination range.  The two measurement ranges are:
0-4000 and 0-125000 Lux. These ranges are reported by the probe
simultaneously to both the fast 10-bit and slow 24-bit input channels
of the probe port. The sensor is a silicon photodiode with an integral
near-IR blocking filter. This sensor gives the light probe a response
mainly in the visible and as such it can is designed for measuring
illumination or the photosynthetically active radiation used by plants
(PAR).</para>

<figure><title>CCLightProbe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/lightprobe.png" format="PNG" depth="240"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
	<phrase>CCLightProbe</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>
</section>
</section>

<section><title>LabBook</title>

<para>Learning requires more than a good tool. Students need to be
guided, challenged to predict, and encouraged to reflect. CCProbe uses
the organizing principle of a lab notebook which contains both
curricular activities and a portfolio of student work.  While CCProbe
includes many traditional probeware tools such as real-time graphing,
analysis, calibration, and saved datasets it also includes software
objects for taking notes, drawing sketches, answering questions, and
displaying images.  CCProbe also supports folders and compound objects
similar to web pages in which the basic objects can be combined
together into activities.  </para>

<para> We call this functionality that CCProbe is built upon the
CCLabBook System.  All the activities and student work are saved in
one place.  Right now we create activities using a structured
XML-based editing system from which CCLabBook objects, html web pages,
and printed pdf versions of the activities are automatically
generated. In the future, teachers will be able to easily modify the
activities or create their own using a web-based authoring
system. Once generated, an activity can be distributed to all
students.  An individual CCLabBook can be easily moved between
handheld and full-size computer systems allowing students to
investigate, edit, and organize information anywhere.  </para>

<para>After a class of students has completed an activity the work
collected in individual CCLabBooks is combined on the teachers
computer where it can be browsed, commented on, and archived.
Additionally, the teacher can place new activities in the student
CCLabBooks.  </para>

<para>An essential design goal of the CCLabBook System is to support
transparent communication of portfolio objects between all these
systems. For example after using CCProbe on a Palm computer to collect
temperature and light data in the field, the LabBook on the Palm can
be saved onto a server where it is accessible from other locations
such as computers in the computer lab.</para>
</section>


<section><title>License</title>

<para>CCProbe is free software that can be downloaded, copied, and
used as you wish. While we retain copyright for all the source code we
have written we specifically provide you with this software with the
GNU General Public License which allows you access to and the right to
modify the source code for CCProbe.  However the GPL license states
that if you distribute the changes in the source code you must also
apply the same license to your copyrighted code.  </para>

<para>Our goal is to create a community of users, researchers and
developers who can contribute towards making CCProbe a more useful
tool.  </para>

</section>

<section><title>Source Code</title>

<para> CCProbe is written in Waba an open source Java-like language
for handhelds.  Waba is its own programming platform including a
language, virtual machine, class file format and set of base classes.
</para>

<para> Because of the way Waba was designed, developers can use Java
development tools to write Waba programs and Waba programs can run as
Java applets or applications with no native code.  </para>

<para> Waba applications can run under Java but, for the most part,
Java programs that use the Java Class Libraries can't run under Waba.
</para>

<para> You can get a copy of of the source code and license by
following the appropriate links at the <ulink
url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware">CCProbeware web site.</ulink>
</para>

</section>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>Installing CCProbe</title>

<para> CCProbe is written in Waba, an open-source GPL licensed subset
of Java specifically designed to work on handheld computers. Normally
when it is run on a Palm or Windows CE system the CCProbe Waba
application is executed by the Waba virtual machine similar to how
Java programs are often run. This is the method used on the PocketPC
version of CCProbe. However on the Palm we use Jump and WabaJump to
compile the Waba application into PalmOS 68000 machine code in order
to operate as fast as possible.  </para>

<para> You can download Packages that contain CCProbe, a LabBook,
documentation, and any OS specific programs needed to run CCProbe by
browsing here: <ulink
url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/ccprobe-downloads.html">CCProbe
Download Page</ulink>.</para>


<para>On MacOS, Windows, and Unix/Linux systems the CCProbe runs as a
Java application using the Waba for Java classes that implement the
Waba API on top of Java. On Unix/Linux systems Waba applications can
run using the Java VM from Sun.  </para>

<table frame='all'><title>Available Packages of CCProbe</title>
<tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
<colspec colname='c1'/>
<colspec colname='c2'/>
<colspec colname='c3'/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Operating System</entry>
<entry>archive type</entry>
<entry>link</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>PalmOS</entry>
<entry>exe for Windows</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-palmos/CCProbe.exe">CCProbe.exe</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>PalmOS</entry>
<entry>tarred and gzipped for Unix</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-palmos/CCProbe.tgz">CCProbe.tgz</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>PalmOS</entry>
<entry>binhex self-extracting archive for MacOS</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-palmos/CCProbe.sea.hqx">CCProbe.sea.hqx</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>PocketPC (for MIPS and StrongArm)</entry>
<entry>exe for Windows</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-pocketpc/CCProbe.exe">CCProbe.exe</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>MacOS Classic</entry>
<entry>binhex self-extracting archive for MacOS</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-macos-classic/CCProbe.sea.hqx">CCProbe.sea.hqx</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>MacOS X</entry>
<entry>binhex self-extracting archive for MacOS</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-macosx/CCProbe.sea.hqx">CCProbe.sea.hqx</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Windows</entry>
<entry>exe for Windows</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-windows/CCProbe.exe">CCProbe.exe</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Linux/Unix</entry>
<entry>tarred and gzipped for Unix</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe/download/ccprobe-unix/CCProbe.tgz">CCProbe.tgz</ulink></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<section><title>MacOS Classic</title>

<para> Installing and running CCProbe on MacOS Classic </para>

<para> CCProbe requires Apple's MacOS Runtime for Java (MRJ). MRJ
implements Sun's Java 1.1 standard. The most recent version of MRJ is
version 2.2.5. Don't be confused by Apple's numbering of their Java
virtual machine. It does not relate to Sun's numbering system for
Java. You can get the latest version of MRJ here: </para>

<para> <ulink url="http://www.info.apple.com/support/downloads.html">
http://www.info.apple.com/support/downloads.html </ulink> </para>

<para> Once you are there do a search for "mrj".  </para>

<para> After installing MRJ you can start the application CCProbe by
double-clicking it.  </para>

<para> Changing the CCProbe application window size </para>

<para> Load the file CCProbe.properties into an program which can edit
a text file such as Eudora, BBEdit, or Simpletext </para>

<para> Look for the following line: </para>

<para> com.apple.mrj.application.parameters=/color /w 600 /h 400
CCProbe </para>

<para> The numbers after the /w and /h set the width and the height of
the application window.  </para>

<para> Edit these numbers and save the file. The next time the CCProbe
application is run it will use the new specification as the window
size.  </para>

<para> Using CCProbe with a Mac that has a USB port </para>

<para> In order to use the CCProbe Interface you will need a
USB-to-Serial Adapter. We have used Keyspan's USA-19 and USA-19W, and
USA-19QW.  In addition you will need a DB9 cable assembly for the
CCProbe Interface.  This consists of a short length of 6-conductor
modular telephone cable, an RJ-11 to DB9 adaptor, and a numll-modem
cable.  </para>

<para> You must install the latest drivers from Keyspan. You can
download them here: </para>

<para> <ulink url="http://www.keyspan.com/downloads/">
http://www.keyspan.com/downloads/ </ulink> </para>

<para> Setting the location of the Serial Communications Port </para>

<para> The first time CCProbe attempts to connect to the CCProbe
interface through the serial port it will ask which serial port to use
to connect to the interface.  If you later need to change this use the
"Serial Port Setup ..." item in the File menu.  </para>

<para> If you use an older Macintosh with a serial port you will most
likely select either the Printer/Modem port or if you have two serial
ports select the Printer port.  If you have troubles connecting make
sure that Appletalk is not already trying to use the serial port by
opening the Appletalk control panel.  If AppleTalk is using a serial
port then you can turn appletalk off with a small control at the
bottom of the Chooser window.  </para>

</section>

<section><title>MacOS X</title>

<para> MacOS X comes with Java 1.3 built in.  After downloading and
expanding the MacOSX CCProbe Package archive double click the RXTX.pkg
installer application.  This will install the RXTX Java serial port
libraries which enable CCProbe to communicate to the serial port.
Once RXTX is installed you can run the CCProbe application directly by
double-clicking the icon.  </para>

</section>

<section><title>Windows</title>

<para> Installing and running CCProbe on Windows </para>

<para> After downloading the CCProbe Package archive for windows run
the ccprobe.exe file to expand the archive.  This will make a folder
named ccprobe-windows.  Before running CCProbe you will need to make
sure that both Java and the Java Communications API are installed.
After installing this software start CCProbe by running CCProbe.bat.
This runs CCWabaLauncher.exe which checks for thepresence of Java and
then runs CCProbe.jar which holds the actual application.  </para>

<para>Installing Java</para>

<para> CCProbe requires Sun's Java 1.1 or higher. You can get the
latest version of the Java 2 Runtime Environment, Standard Edition for
Windows here: </para>

<para> <ulink
url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.3/jre/download-windows.html">
http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.3/jre/download-windows.html </ulink>
</para>

<para> Even though it is called Java 2, Sun's internal numbering calls
this Java version 1.3.1.  </para>

<para> In addition to Java the Java Communications API must be
installed to support serial communications with the interface.
</para>

<para> 1. Install the Java Communications API </para>

<para> In order to install the following components you must determine
where the java home directory is on your system. On my Windows 2000
system it is C:\Program Files\JavaSoft\1.3.1. In the procedure below
replace occurances of javahome with the location of the java home
directory on your system.  </para>

<para> The home page for the Java Communications API is: </para>

<para> <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/javacomm/">
http://java.sun.com/products/javacomm/ </ulink> </para>

<para> Download Version 2.0 for Microsoft Windows.  </para> 

<para> The Java Communications API will be saved on your computer in a
ZIP archive. You will need a utility to expand the archive. The free
program FreeZip works well. You can get it here: </para>

<para> <ulink
url="http://crnet.tucows.com/system/preview/194266.html">
http://crnet.tucows.com/system/preview/194266.html </ulink> </para>


<para> Most of the items are not needed however copy the three items
below: </para>

<para> a. Copy win32com.dll to the javahome\bin
directory </para> 



<para> b. Copy comm.jar to the javahome\lib\ext </para>

<para> c. Place javax.comm.properties in the javahome\lib </para>

<para> Specifying the location of the Serial Communications Port
</para>

<para> The first time CCProbe attempts to connect to the
CCProbe interface through the serial port it will ask which serial
port to use to connect to the interface.  If you later need to change
this use the "Serial Port Setup ..." item in the File menu.  </para>


<para> Changing the CCProbe application window size </para>

<para> Load the file CCProbe.bat into an program which can edit a text
file such as WordPad </para>

<para> Edit the first line in the file: </para>

<para> java -cp CCProbe.jar waba.applet.Applet /w 600 /h 400 /color
CCProbe </para>

<para> The numbers after the /w and /h set the width and the height of
the application window.  Edit these numbers and save the file. The
next time the CCProbe application is run it will use the new
specification as the window size.  </para> 

</section>

<section><title>Unix/Linux</title>

<para> After downloading and expanding the Unix tar archive of the
CCProbe Package run the RXTX.pkg installer application.  This will
install the RXTX Java serial port libraries which enable CCProbe to
communicate to the serial port.  Once RXTX is installed you can run
the CCProbe application directly by double-clicking the icon.</para>

</section>

<section><title>PocketPC</title>

<para> CCProbe requires that you have the Waba virtual machine
installed.  The Waba vm consists of two files: waba.exe and waba.wrp.
The waba.exe file is specific to the processor used in the PocketPC.
</para>

<para> On either system create a new folder called waba here: </para>

<para>
My Device:Program Files:waba
</para>

<para>
Place the appropriate waba.exe and waba.wrp file in the waba folder.
</para>

<para>
iPaq		waba-strongarm/waba.exe
</para>

<para>
Casiopeia	waba-mips/waba.exe
</para>

<para>
The waba.wrp is identical on both systems.
</para>

<para>
Now copy the link and waba executable files to the same directory:
</para>

<para>
CCProbe.lnk
</para>

<para>
CCProbe.wrp
</para>

<para>
There will now be two files named CCProbe in the waba folder on your
PocketPC.  Start CCProbe by tapping on the CCProbe link file.  This
file is under 1k in size, it is much smaller than the waba executable.
</para>

</section>

<section><title>PalmOS</title>

<para> After downloading and expanding the PalmOS archive approriate
for your operating system install the Palm application CCProbe.prc and
the Palm database LabBook.PDB using the standard tools on your system
for installing Palm applications.  </para>

<para>On Windows and MacOS systems the Palm Desktop software from Palm
is normally used to install applications on a Palm.  First select the
two files: CCProbe.prc and LabBook.PDB to be installed then connect
your Palm to the computer through either it's cradle or through a
hotsynch cable and start the synch process.  Synching is started on
the Palm by either pressing theHotSynch button on the cradle or
openeing the HotSynch applicationon the Palm and tapping on the
HotSynch button on the screen.</para>

<para>On Unix/Linux systems the program pilot-xfer is usually used to
install applications and databases on a Palm.  The pilot-xfer program
is part of a suite of tools called pilot-link.</para>

<para>On MacOS X the pilot-link Unix tools can be used and a beta
version of the Palm desktop is available.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Updating your version of CCProbe</title>

<para>There are two parts to CCProbe: the application, and the
LabBook.  You can always get the latest stable release as a package by
going to the 

<ulink
url="http://concord.org/ccprobeware/ccprobe-download.html">CCProbe download page</ulink>


</para>

</section>
</chapter>


<chapter><title>CCProbe LabBook</title>

<para>The LabBook functions as both a place for embedding curricula
and a portfolio for holding and organizing student work.  The TEEMSS
project at the Consord Consortium has developed an extensive
curriculum for Middle School science studies with five investigations
on Motions and Forces and another five on Energy Transformations.
Currently we distribute this LabBook with CCProbe.</para>

<para>LabBooks are portable, they can be communicated between all the
different computer systems that CCProbe runs on.  Data collected on a
Palm in the field can easily be transferred to and displayed on a
desktop system at home.  And conversely material written on a LabBook
on a larger computer with a keyborad can be transferred back to the
LabBookon the handheld system.</para>

<para>A LabBook can hold many different kinds of software objects
including folders for organizing other objects, data collectors,
drawings, notes for writing, images, a tool for unit conversion, and a
compound html-like object we call a Supernote.</para>

 
<section id="labbook_views"><title>LabBook Views</title>

<para>When the CCProbe is started it will open the default LabBook
file.  On PalmOS this is the PalmOS database LabBook.PDB.  On a
desktop OS this is the file LabBook.PDB in the same folder where the
CCProbe application resides.  On a Windows CE or PocketPC system the
file is named LabBook and is located in the top level of the
filesystem under "My Devices"</para>

<figure>
    <title>TEEMSS CCProbe LabBook: initial display (PalmOS)</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/ccprobe-palm-start-1.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>The two visible items in the LabBook are folders "CCProbe" and
"TEEMSS".  These folders are enclosed by an implicit folder named
Home. Each of these folders display in a tree view by default when
opened. Just to the left of these folders are little triangles called
twisties.  Tap on a twistie to display the contents of the folder in
tree view.
</para>

<section><title>Tree View</title>

<para>
<xref linkend="teemss_ccprobe_labbook_teems_folder_opened_palmos"/> shows
the result of tapping on the TEEMSS twistie and then tapping on the
Motions and Forces  twistie.  Inside Motions and Forces  are displayed
the individual investigations.  All of the object displayed below are
folders. So far everything is being displayed in a tree view.</para>

<figure id="teemss_ccprobe_labbook_teems_folder_opened_palmos">
    <title>TEEMSS CCProbe LabBook: TEEMS folder opened (PalmOS)</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/ccprobe-teems-open-palm.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>Instead of displaying the whole folder hierarchy in tree mode
select the Motions and Forces folder and tap the Open button. Figure 
<xref linkend="teemss_ccprobe_labbook_mf_folder_opened_palmos"/>
displays the objects in the Motions and Forces folder.  Each item is a
folder which is a TEEMSS investigation.</para>

<figure id="teemss_ccprobe_labbook_mf_folder_opened_palmos">
    <title>TEEMSS CCProbe LabBook: Motions and Forces folder opened (PalmOS)</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/ccprobe-mf-open-palm.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>


<para>If you open the TEEMSS investigation folders they will display
in page view instead of tree view.  Page view makes it easier to
sequence through a group of LabBook objects.  However if you tap on a
twistie next to one of the investigation folders you can see what is
included in a tree view.
</para>


<figure id="teemss_ccprobe_labbook_tracker_folder_opened_palmos">
    <title>TEEMSS CCProbe LabBook: Tracker folder opened in tree view (PalmOS)</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/ccprobe-tracker-tree-palm.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>In order to move back up the tree hierarchy to the original
location tap on the folder-path menu in the top left corner of the
screen as shown in <xref
linkend="teemss_ccprobe_labbook_tracker_tree_up_opened_palmos"/>.  Tap
on Home to return to the top level.</para>

<figure id="teemss_ccprobe_labbook_tracker_tree_up_opened_palmos">
    <title>TEEMSS CCProbe LabBook: getting back to Home (PalmOS)</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/ccprobe-tracker-tree-up-palm.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>All of the objects in the investigation are displayed and they
can be opened directly by either selecting and tapping the Open button
or double-tapping the object directtly.  However because TEEMSS
investigations are designed to be used in a sequenced order it is
better to open the Tracker investigation itself.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Paging View</title>

<para>The TEEMSS investigations are all designed to be used in a
paging view.  Open the Tracker investigation by either double-tapping
Tracker or selecting Tracker and tapping the Open button.  </para>

<figure id="teemss_ccprobe_labbook_tracker_intro_palmos">
    <title>TEEMSS CCProbe LabBook: Tracker Introduction (PalmOS)</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/png/ccprobe-tracker-intro-palm.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para><xref linkend="teemss_ccprobe_labbook_tracker_intro_palmos"/>
shows the first object in the Tracker folder, the SuperNote
"Introduction".  At the top left of the screen are buttons labeled
"Prev" and "Next".  To the right of these buttons is a pulldown menu
which lists all the objects in the Tracker Investigation.</para>

<para>Tap the "Next" button to move from the Introduction to the next
element of the investigation called "Thinking About the Question".</para>

</section>

</section>
<section><title>LabBook Objects</title>

<para>All of the following objects can be combined to create
curricular activities or as a portfolio of work.  LabBook objetcs can
be created, named, copied and pasted, and deleted from within CCProbe.
</para>

<section><title>Folders</title>

<para>Objects in a LabBook can be organized into folders which
themselves are another type of LabBook object.  Folders have a display
property of either Tree or Paging.  See <xref
linkend="labbook_views"/> for more information on folder display properties.
</para>

</section>

<section><title>DataCollectors</title>

<para>CCProbe comes with five different types of DataCollectors:
Temperature, Force, SmartWheel, VoltageCurrent, and Light.  These are
the objects in the LabBook which combine collection and display of of
real-time data from the probes.  In addition to real-time graphing
DataCollectors support annotation of points on the graph, display of
annotated points as a bar graph, flexible axis scaling and
translation, and note taking.  After collecting data the data can be
saved as a DataSet for later display or analysis.</para>

</section> 

<section><title>DataSets</title>

<para>DataSets are LabBook objects that hold saved collections of data
from a DataCollector.  A DataSet will save the data from a collection
until the DataSet object is deleted.  All the graph display and
annotation tools available in a DataCollector are also available in a
DataSet.  </para> 

</section> 
<section><title>Drawings</title> 

<para> Freehand drawings and sketches can be created in a LabBook
Drawing object.  The pen color can be set and an eraser tool is
available.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Notes</title>

<para>A LabBook Notes object holds writing.  At this point when you
are writing into a note you must type the Return character at the end
of the line in order to continue writing on thenext line below.  The
Note object will not automatically wrap entered text onto the next
line.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Unit Convertors</title>

<para>In order to more easily do calculations with different units we
have a Unit Comnvertor calculator.  This allows conversions from and
to many different physical quantities.</para> 

</section>

<section><title>Images</title>

<para>On desktop systems images can be loaded into LabBook Image
objects.  After loading into the LabBook the images can be displayed
on any system that CCProbe runs on.  On the Palm IIIc which only has
256 colors we use the Netscape 216 web color pallete for displayed
images.  CCProbe can import ".bmp" images and if it is running on a
Macintosh it can import a wide variety of images using
QuickTime.</para>


</section>
<section><title>Supernotes</title>

<para>CCProbe supports a compund document object we call a Supernote.
A Supernote is similar to an html document and can hold text, links to
other objects and even the objects themselves embedded directly in a
Supernote.  Supernote creation and editing can be done on a dektop
system.  Advanced Supernote creation can more easily be done by
writing the object structure in XML and creating the LabBook with the
XML2LabBook conversion tool.</para>

</section>
</section>

<section><title>File Menu</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>New..</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Open..</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Renaming</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Exporting</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Importing</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Deleting</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>About CCProbe</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Exit</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section><title> Edit Menu</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Cut</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Paste</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Properties</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Toggle Hidden </title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter><title>Managing a LabBook</title>

<section><title>Transferring LabBooks and LabBook objects</title>

<section><title>Synching with PalmOS computers</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Exporting and Importing LabBook objects</title>

<para>LabBook objects including folders can be exported and imported
on desktop operating systems.

On versions of CCProbe that run desktop operating systsem
</para>

</section>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter><title>DataCollectors</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Graphing data with CCProbe</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Saving Data in a DataSet</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Exporting Data</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Multiple Data Collections</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Clearing the Data</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Marking and Labeling the Graph</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Saving Notes With the DataSet</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Viewing as a Bar Graph</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Changing the Axes and Moving the graph</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Selecting an area and Zooming In</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>DataCollector Properties Dialog</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Y Axis Properties</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>X Axis Properties</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Graph Properties</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Probe Properties</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Calibration Dialog</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section><title>Types of DataCollectors</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Temperature</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Connecting the Temperature Probe</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Output Mode: C, F, K</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Calibration</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section><title>Light</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Connecting the Light Probe</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Output Mode</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Calibration</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section><title>SmartWheel</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Connecting the SmartWheel Probe</title>

<para>
</para>
</section>

<section><title>Port Selection: A</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Output Mode</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Calibration</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section><title>Force</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Connecting the Force Probe</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Output Mode</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Calibration</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section><title>Voltage/Current</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Connecting the Voltage/Current Probe</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Output Mode</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Calibration</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section><title>RawData</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Using the RawData DataCollector</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Port Selection: A or B</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Output Mode</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Calibration</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>
</section>

<section><title>File Menu</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Beam</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Save Data</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Export Data</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>About CCProbe</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Exit</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>

<section><title>Edit</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Properties</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Save Profile</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>DataSets</title>

<para>
</para>

</chapter>

<chapter><title>Drawings</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Drawing</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Erasing</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Clearing the Whole Picture</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Setting the Pen Color</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>Unit Convertors</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Length</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Mass</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Time</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Temperature</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Area</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
<section><title>Volume</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Energy</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Force</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Power</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Pressure</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Electricity</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>Images</title>

<para>
</para>

</chapter>

<chapter><title>Supernotes</title>

<para>
</para>

</chapter>

<chapter><title>LabBook Management</title>

<para>
</para>

</chapter>

<chapter><title>Advanced Features</title>

<para>
</para>

<section><title>Folder Modes</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>

<section><title>Editing Supernotes</title>

<para>
</para>

</section>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>Reporting Bugs and Feature Requests</title>

<para>
</para>

</chapter>

<chapter><title>CCProbe Development</title>

<para>
</para>

</chapter>

</book>
