<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE project PUBLIC "-//CONCORD.ORG//DTD Param Description//EN" "project.dtd">
<project name="teemss">
  <title>TEEMSS</title>
  <skill-list>
	<skill name="learn stuff">I'm learning xsl haha</skill>
	<skill name="learn other stuff">Of course that means I'm learning XML too.</skill>
  </skill-list>
  <unit name="Motions_and_Forces">
    <title>Motions and Forces</title>
    <investigation name="Air_Cart">
      <title>Air Cart</title>
	  <teacher-notes>
		<teacher-intro>
		  <summary>Testing testing </summary>
		  <skills>
			<skill-ref ref="learn stuff"/>
			<skill-ref ref="learn other stuff"/>
		  </skills>
		</teacher-intro>
		<teacher-discuss>
		  <teacher-overview>This investigation is important because students build a low-friction cart and ramp that will be needed later. Most of this investigation is devoted to construction and testing. This can be most absorbing, but to get the most out of the time, you should encourage students to think about the goal of friction reduction and how the cart design achieves this.
</teacher-overview>
		  <teacher-stage>Before beginning the construction, engage students in a conversation about friction. A good first discussion can be about what it would be like to exist in a world without friction. Here are some questions you might ask, followed by possible responses.
<teacher-questions>
			  <question>When have you experienced very low friction?</question>
			  <answer>Roller-skating, ice skating, skateboarding. Not swimming</answer>
			  <question>What would it be like if every surface was covered by slippery ice?</question>
			  <answer>It would be hard to stand up. Going down stairs would be very dangerous--hanging on the banister would not help much because your hands would slip, too.</answer>
			  <question>Would your bike work in a frictionless world?</question>
			</teacher-questions>
</teacher-stage>
		  <teacher-wrap>If students investigate the effect of mass, they might be in for a surprise. It is natural to assume that the heavier cart will zoom down the ramp faster. Ask students:
</teacher-wrap>
		</teacher-discuss>
		<teacher-background>
The energy lost to friction always ends up as heat energy in the form of random molecular motion. This will come up in later investigations, when the question "where did the energy go?" will be asked again and again. There can be many sources of friction. In the case of the cart, the axle rubs in the straw when it turns. There is some rolling friction as the wheel surface touches and then lifts from the floor. This is much less than if the wheels were locked and dragged across the floor, however! That's why car brakes work: when the wheel is braked, it is dragged along the road instead of being free to roll. It's also why you can steer: it's easier for a wheel to roll in the direction it's steered than to slide sideways, so the car tends to go in that direction, unless the road is icy.
</teacher-background>
		<teacher-timeline>
		  <time-period periods="1" type="setup"/>
		  <time-period periods="1.5" type="trial" number="1"/>
		  <time-period periods=".5" type="trial" number="2"/>
		  <time-period periods="1" type="wrap"/>
		</teacher-timeline>
	  </teacher-notes>
      <summary> Build (and test) an air cart that operates with very
        little friction</summary>
      <question> What happens to a vehicle when there&apos;s very little friction?</question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="smallCart"/> In this
        activity you will build and test an air cart that operates with
        very little friction.</intro>
      <think>
        <p> Have you ever wondered why cars stay on the road when they
          round a corner? Why is it more difficult to round those
          corners when the road is wet or covered with ice? Besides the
          banking of the road (which we will learn about later), the
          tires provide a frictional surface against the surface of the
          road. The ideal car provides friction when you need it
          (turning and braking) but has little when you don&apos;t want
          it (speeding along in a straight line). </p>
        <p> It&apos;s not that easy to make a vehicle move with almost
          no friction. But that&apos;s the goal of this investigation.
          We want a cart that&apos;s almost friction free so that we can
          study the forces on moving objects without being confused by
          the forces due to friction. If a frictionless cart, for
          example, is pushed across the floor, how far do you think the
          cart will go? In your group, predict and explain how different
          forces will affect the motion of a frictionless cart. Write in
          Notes on your handheld computer your ideas about what might
          explain your prediction(s). Refer to Technical Hints to see
          how to use the software. </p>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="00_cartParts" type="gif"/>
        <item>CC SmartWheel</item>
        <item>cardboard for cart body (12cm x 40cm)</item>
        <item>cardboard for ramp (30cm x 100cm)</item>
        <item>2 - junk CD-ROMs, with snap-in plastic hubs</item>
        <item>aluminum axle (15cm)</item>
        <item>drinking straw</item>
        <item>rubber bumper (popper)</item>
        <item>small paper drinking cup (150 ml)</item>
        <item>small DC motor with leads</item>
        <item>propeller</item>
        <item>2 - new 1.5V AA batteries</item>
        <item>battery holder with leads</item>
        <item>clay (for added weight)</item>
        <item>accelerator acrobat</item>
        <item>wire for support of accelerator acrobat</item>
        <item>books to prop up ramp</item>
        <item>tape</item>
        <item>handheld computer</item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software</item>
        <item>hot-melt (or cold-melt) glue gun and glue sticks</item>
        <item>utility knife</item>
        <item>metal straight edge ruler (metric)</item>
        <item>scissors</item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item> If you are using a hot glue gun, caution should be taken
          until the glue cools and hardens. Burns may result.</item>
        <item> If you are using a utility knife to cut the cardboard,
          extreme care should be taken to prevent cuts. Use a sharp
          blade and get instruction in how to cut against a straightedge.</item>
        <item> If you choose to use the propeller, keep in mind that it
          turns rapidly when it is powered by the battery, so watch out
          for your fingers!</item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Building an air cart"> To build your air cart follow
        these easy steps! <instructions>
          <instruction title="Making the cardboard foundation">
            <steps>
              <step> Carefully use the utility knife to cut out a 12cm x
                40cm rectangle from cardboard for the air cart body. The
                corrugations in the cardboard should run the long way.
                Your teacher may provide this cardboard piece already cut.</step>
              <step> Mark the slot for the SmartWheel probe. Be sure the
                slot is parallel to the cart length. The slot is 2cm
                wide and 14cm long, starting 4cm from one end of the cart.</step>
              <step> Cut out the slot with a utility knife. Please be
                very careful! <ext-image-sequence>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="01a_cardboard"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="01b_slotCutMark"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="01c_slotCutOut"/>
                </ext-image-sequence>
              </step>
            </steps>
          </instruction>
          <instruction title="Installing the axles">
            <steps>
              <step>Mark the axle line. It is 8cm from the other end of
                the cart and perpendicular to the long side. You can use
                the corner of a piece of paper to make a perpendicular line.</step>
              <step>Glue the straw to the axle line with hot-melt glue.
                Let it stick out on either side.  </step>
              <step>Cut off each end of the straw a bit longer than the cardboard.</step>
              <step>The finished straw is now ready for the axle.<ext-image-sequence>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="02a_strawMark"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="02b_strawGlued"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="02c_strawCut"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="02d_strawInstall"/>
                </ext-image-sequence>
              </step>
            </steps>
          </instruction>
          <instruction title="Attaching the SmartWheel to the Cart">
            <steps>
              <step>Center the SmartWheel in the slot so that it
                doesn&apos;t rub against the cardboard. Make it exactly
                parallel to the long edge of the cart. This will make
                the cart go straight. The aluminum arm goes against the
                same side of the cardboard as the straw. Mark two screw
                holes with a pencil or pen, one at each end.  </step>
              <step>Make holes where the marks are, using a pencil or
                pen point. Enlarge the holes from both sides, until the
                screws fit snugly into them. The screws are provided
                with the SmartWheel.</step>
              <step>Put the screws through the cardboard from the other
                side, and screw them into the arm of the SmartWheel.
                Tighten them until the heads squeeze the cardboard a
                little bit. A paper clip will work as a screwdriver. </step>
              <step>Now the SmartWheel is in place. It can be taken on
                and off. You will need to do this for the Tracker Investigation.<ext-image-sequence>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="03a_swMarkHoles" type="gif"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="03b_makeHoles" type="gif"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="03c_swScrews" type="gif"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="03d_swInstalled" type="gif"/>
                </ext-image-sequence>
              </step>
            </steps>
          </instruction>
          <instruction title="Attaching the CD ROM wheels to the cart">
            <steps>
              <step>Snap each CD ROM wheel onto a black hub, if this
                isn&apos;t already done. Put the hub on a table with the
                tapered end pointing up, and push the CD wheel down,
                snapping it into place.  </step>
              <step>Push the aluminum axle into the black hub on one CD
                ROM wheel. The long tapered end of the black hub should
                face toward the cart.   </step>
              <step>Slide the axle through the straw and then slide on
                the other CD ROM wheel. The picture shows the cart
                upside down.  <ext-image-sequence>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="04a_pressInHub" type="gif"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart"
		  name="04b_oneWheelAxle" type="gif"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="04c_wheelPair" type="gif"/>
                </ext-image-sequence>
              </step>
            </steps>
          </instruction>
          <instruction title="Glueing on the bumper">
            <p>Glue the bumper in             the center on the front
              end that contains the SmartWheel end.<ext-image name="05_bumper"/>
            </p>
          </instruction>
          <instruction title="Attaching the motor">
            <steps>
              <step>Glue the motor on the back end, in the center, with
                its body sticking out a little bit beyond the cardboard.
                Use plenty of glue. </step>
              <step>Place the batteries in the battery holder. Make sure
                the batteries are loaded in opposite directions in the
                holder. Glue it down in the center next to the motor.
                Leave a little bit of space between the battery holder
                and the motor.  <ext-image-sequence>
                  <ext-image dir="images/aircart" name="06a_motor"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="06b_batteries"/>
                </ext-image-sequence>
              </step>
            </steps>
          </instruction>
          <instruction title="Glueing on the clay holder">
            <p>Glue down the             paper cup in the center right
              behind the SmartWheel slot.             Make a lump of
              clay so that you can add weight to the cart.  <ext-image name="07_clayHolder"/>
            </p>
          </instruction>
          <instruction title="Attaching the acrobat and holder ">
            <steps>
              <step>To make the swinging bar for the acrobat, first bend
                the wire into a &quot;U&quot; about 6cm wide and 17cm
                long.  </step>
              <step>Bend up the ends of the &quot;U&quot; and crimp them
                a little bit. Each crimped end should be about 4cm. long.</step>
              <step>Slide the crimped ends into the corrugated
                cardboard. If the ends of the wire are crimped, they
                will fit snugly into the end of the corrugated cardboard
                and stay firm during collisions. The acrobat needs to be
                removed when you mount the Force probe on the cart.  </step>
              <step>Put bits of clay into the acrobat&apos;s hands so
                that it has a good grip. Hang the acrobat on the wire.  <ext-image-sequence>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="08a_wireU"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="08b_wireCrimped"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="08c_wireAttach"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="08d_wireAcrobat"/>
                </ext-image-sequence>
              </step>
            </steps>
          </instruction>
          <instruction title="Decorating your cart ">
            <p>Decorate your cart             to your liking...
                <ext-image name="09_cartDone" type="gif"/>
            </p>
          </instruction>
        </instructions>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Building a test ramp">
        <steps>
          <step>You will need to build a ramp to provide your cart an
            equal start, again and again.  <steps>
              <step>Cut a piece of cardboard about 1m long and at least
                30cm wide. </step>
              <step>Mark two lines 5cm from each side of the cardboard.  </step>
              <step>Along the two lines, fold the cardboard into a
                &quot;U&quot; to make the edges stiff and keep the cart
                from running off the edge. </step>
              <step>Then the cardboard ramp rests easily on a flat surface.<ext-image-sequence>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="10a_rampSize"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="10b_rampMark"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCart" name="10c_rampFold"/>
                  <ext-image dir="images/AirCarts" name="10d_rampEnd"/>
                </ext-image-sequence>
              </step>
            </steps>
          </step>
          <step>To use the ramp, you will need to prop one end up with
            books. One simple way to measure the slope of the ramp is to
            give the ratio of the height of one end to the length. Thus,
            if the ramp end is raised 10cm and it is 1 meter long, its
            slope is about 1:10, or 10 percent. Don&apos;t raise it much
            more than this. The cart will go too fast!<p>HINT: How
              should you measure how far &quot;up&quot; the cart is when
              you release it? The distance along the ramp from its
              bottom edge to the rear wheels of the cart is a good
              measure.  <ext-image name="11a_rampSideView"/>
            </p>
          </step>
          <step>Experiment with different slopes and distances up the
            ramp. How does each affect how far the cart will roll? What
            arrangement is the best for testing the friction of the
            cart? Write in Notes on your handheld computer your thoughts
            about the best arrangement of your ramp.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Performing a coasting test">
        <steps>
          <step>Propose a way to test the relative friction of the
            carts, without using the motor and fan. You can use the
            ramp, however. HINT: Decide on a distance, a way to start
            together, and a way to compare your cart with at least three
            other carts. Should they all race together on separate
            ramps, or race one by one and compare them? Do they get more
            than one run?  </step>
          <step>Do you think this is a fair test of the friction of the
            cart? Explain your prediction in Notes on your handheld
            computer. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the
            software.  </step>
          <step>Race your air cart with at least three other carts by
            rolling them down the ramp. Observe the motion of the
            acrobat during the race.</step>
          <step>What is your measure of friction? Which one has the
            least friction? Explain your thoughts and observations in
            Notes on your handheld computer. Refer to Technical Hints to
            see how to use the software.  <ext-image
              dir="images/AirCart" name="12_rampRace"/>
          </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Opening and using CC software</title>
          <heading>To open and use CC Lab Book software:</heading>
          <body>Coming Soon!</body>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step> Rank your cart and at least two others in order of how
          they did on the friction test. What differences in the carts
          might account for this?</step>
	  <step> When your cart is moving, it has energy of motion. What
          factors do you think affect its energy? When your cart slows
          down and stops, where does the energy go? What about when it
          hits something?</step>
	  <step>What happened to the motion of the acrobat when the cart
          slowed down? What about when the cart hit something?   </step>
	  <step>In summary, how does a vehicle behave when there&apos;s
          very little friction? Does it take a lot of force to get it
          going? To keep it going? </step>
	  <step>What are the sources of friction for these carts? Do you
          think air resistance plays a role? How could you find out?   </step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>What slows the cart down? Investigate ways to reduce the
          friction of your cart. Your cart should use the SmartWheel,
          but anything else about it can be changed. Provide reasons for
          your design choices. Which changes will have the greatest
          decrease in friction?  </item>
        <item>Decide on a way to compare the friction of different
          carts. Why is this a fair test? Compare various carts and see
          if you can understand what the differences are that make them
          have more or less friction. Do they test the same every time?  </item>
        <item>Play the sabotage game. Investigate ways to increase the
          friction of your (or your opponent&apos;s) cart.   </item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
    <investigation name="Tracker">
      <title>Tracker</title>
      <summary>Explore the relationship between the movement of a cart
        and the shapes of the resulting position and velocity graphs</summary>
      <question>What does a graph of the motion of a low-friction cart
        look like?</question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image name="smallSmartCart"/>In this activity you will
        explore the relationship between the movement of a cart and the
        shapes of the resulting position and velocity graphs.</intro>
      <think> Can you tell exactly how far or fast your cart is moving
        without using a meter stick and stop watch? How do you know
        it&apos;s speed at any given time? By watching your cart move,
        is it possible to know when it is slowing down? Would it be more
        useful to know its speed at each moment, or its position? Could
        you get one from the other? Discuss these questions with your
        group and write down some of your ideas in Notes on your
        handheld computer to share with your group.<p>The following
          position versus time graph of a cart was made with a
          SmartWheel. Discuss the motion shown with your group. Did the
          cart appear to change velocity at anytime? Draw the graph in
          Notes on your handheld computer and label parts of the graph
          that you understand or have questions about.   </p>
        <ext-image name="graconstant" type="jpg"/>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <item>CC SmartWheel probe removed from air cart</item>
        <item>meter stick</item>
        <item>tape</item>
        <item>CC SmartWheel probe installed on air cart</item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software</item>
        <item>handheld computer</item>
        <item>constructed air cart (see Investigation: Air Cart)  </item>
        <item>2 - new 1.5V AA batteries</item>
        <item>string (for pulling cart) </item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item>No specific safety features needed for this investigation.</item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Walking off distances">
        <steps>
          <step>Remove the SmartWheel from your cart. Carefully save the
            two screws. Tape or screw the SmartWheel to the end of a
            meter stick so that you can walk along and roll it on the
              floor.<ext-image name="01a_swTaped2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Connect the SmartWheel to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the cables.</step>
          <step>Start the software and observe the position versus time
            graph as you roll the SmartWheel along the floor. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to use the software.  <ext-image name="02_swOnWand"/>
          </step>
          <step>With your team member, take turns making the following
            motions on the same graph. <steps>
              <step>walking forward at a constant velocity</step>
              <step>walking forward, then backward, at constant velocity</step>
              <step>walking forward slowly, then quickly, then stopping</step>
              <step>gradually speeding up, then gradually slowing down</step>
            </steps>
          </step>
          <step>Save your data to the handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Describe the portions of the graph for each set of
            movements in Notes on your handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Rolling cart">
        <steps>
          <step>Reattach the SmartWheel to your cart. </step>
          <step>Connect the SmartWheel to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the cables.  </step>
          <step>Attach a string to the front of your cart. It can be
            looped around the bumper.<ext-image name="03A_tr"/>
          </step>
          <step>Practice pulling the cart while draping the connecting
            cable above the cart so that it doesn&apos;t pull the cart
            one way or the other. One person will need to walk alongside
            the cart while carrying the handheld computer and keeping
            the wire from obstructing the movement of the
              cart.<ext-image name="03b_tr"/>
          </step>
          <step>
            <query-response type="describe" layout="list" title="cart movements">
              <query-description> Draw and then describe in words each of the following movements of your cart.
              </query-description>
              <querys>
                <query drawing-response="true" note-response="true">
                  pulling the cart forward at a constant velocity.
                </query>
                <query drawing-response="true" note-response="true">
                  pulling the cart at a slow constant velocity, then a
                  faster constant velocity, then coasting
                </query>
                <query drawing-response="true" note-response="true">
                  speeding up the cart, then coasting
                </query>
                <query drawing-response="true" note-response="true">
                  pulling the cart, then letting it bounce off a wall
                </query>
              </querys>
            </query-response>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software and observe the position versus time
            graph as you make the following motions on the same graph.
            Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the software. 
            <steps>
              <step>pulling the cart forward at a constant velocity</step>
              <step>pulling the cart at a slow constant velocity, then a
                faster constant velocity, then coasting</step>
              <step>gradually speeding up the cart, then coasting</step>
              <step>pulling the cart, then letting it bounce off a wall </step>
            </steps>
          </step>
          <step>Save your data to the handheld computer.</step>
          <step>Discuss the following questions with your group and
            write down some of your ideas in Notes on your handheld
            computer. What do the graphs show you about the motion of
            the cart? How did the acrobat respond during the constant
            motion and the changing motion?</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Rolling to a stop">
        <steps>
          <step>
            <query-response type="explain" layout="paragraph" title="ramp">
              <query-description> 
                Using the ramp to initiate motion of the cart, design a
                method to slow down the cart and bring it to a stop in
                exactly 5 seconds as it rolls across a rug or another rough
                surface. 
              </query-description>
              <querys>
                <query drawing-response="true" note-response="true">
                  Explain your design in Notes on your handheld computer.
                </query>
              </querys>
            </query-response>
          </step>
          <step>In Notes on your handheld computer, predict and sketch
            the resulting position versus time graph. Share your method
            with other members of your group.  </step>
          <step>
            <query-response type="predict" layout="paragraph" title="position-time graph">
              <query-description> 
                  What will the position versus time graph look like?               </query-description>
              <querys>
                <query drawing-response="true" note-response="true">
                  What will the position versus time graph look like? Sketch the graph in In Notes on your handheld computer. 
                </query>
              </querys>
            </query-response>
          </step>

          <step>Connect the SmartWheel to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the cables.</step>
          <step>Now try your method out. Start the software and observe
            the position versus time graph as you roll the cart down the
            ramp. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the
            software. Be sure to drape the wire to the SmartWheel so
            that the cart rolls freely. Observe how the acrobat
            responded during the motion.</step>
          <step>Save your data to the handheld.<ext-image name="04_tr2"/>
          </step>
          <step>By looking at your position versus time graph, how do
            you know that your cart slowed down? Did it slow down at the
            same rate for the entire 5 seconds? If not, when and why did
            the rate change? Explain your reasoning in Notes on your
            handheld computer.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Connecting cables from the SmartWheel to the handheld computer</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Attaching SmartWheel to air cart</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Opening saved data in the CC Lab Book software  </title>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step>What does the steepness of the position versus time graph
          tell you about the velocity of the cart? How can you tell from
          the graph whether the cart is going forward or backward?  </step>
	  <step>What is the shape of the distance versus time graphs of a
          cart as it moves at:  <steps>
	      <step>constant velocity?  </step>
	      <step>decreasing velocity?</step>
	      <step>increasing velocity?  </step>
	    </steps>
        </step>
	  <step>Explain the differences of movement of the acrobat during
          Trial II and Trial III. What happened to either make it move
          or keep it still during each motion?  </step>
	  <step>Display each graph as a velocity versus time graph. See
          Technical Hints on how to switch between position and velocity
          graphs. How are the position and velocity graphs related for
          each trial? What is the shape of the velocity versus time
          graph of a cart as it moves at:<steps>
	      <step>constant velocity?</step>
	      <step>decreasing velocity?  </step>
	      <step>increasing velocity?</step>
	    </steps>
        </step>
	  <step>Do you think that if you knew the position of the cart at
          every moment, you could know its velocity as well?</step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>Draw a position graph of a motion that you would like your
          cart to do. Try to replicate the graph by moving your cart
          with the SmartWheel attached and the software set to read
          position.  </item>
        <item>Draw a velocity graph of a motion that you would like your
          cart to move. Try to replicate the graph by moving your cart
          with the SmartWheel attached and the software set to read velocity.</item>
        <item>Try pushing the cart up the ramp and then letting it roll
          back down the ramp. Predict what you think the position and
          speed graphs will look like and then test your prediction.  </item>
        <item>Try keeping your cart moving at a constant velocity for 30
          seconds. Describe how this could be done and test your method
          out. Examine the resulting position versus time graph. </item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
    <investigation name="Propeller">
      <title>Propeller</title>
      <summary>Investigate how friction and the driving force of a
        propeller mounted on an air cart oppose one another </summary>
      <question>What are the effects of friction on the motion of the
        propeller-driven cart?</question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image name="propellerCartRev"/>In this activity you will
        investigate how friction and the driving force of a propeller
        mounted on an air cart oppose one another.  </intro>
      <think>If you sneeze in a weightless environment, as some of the
        astronauts have done, your body would move backwards and
        upwards. In order for a motion to happen, a force is needed. So,
        why does an astronaut&apos;s body move when they sneeze? Write
        (or draw) in Notes on your handheld computer the forces that
        occur during the sneeze. <p>Picture a propeller or fan blowing
          air. What is accelerating the air? How does the accelerating
          air from the propeller relate to your description of the
          forces found during a sneeze in space? Will your almost
          frictionless cart move when the propeller is turned on? Will
          it still move when you add more friction? Write (or draw) in
          Notes on your handheld computer the forces that you think will
          make the cart move.   </p>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <item>CC SmartWheel probe installed on air cart</item>
        <item>handheld computer  </item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software</item>
        <item>constructed air cart (see Investigation: Air Cart)  </item>
        <item>paper clip</item>
        <item>string or small, thin rubber band  </item>
        <item>2 - new 1.5V AA batteries</item>
        <item>scissors</item>
        <item>file card</item>
        <item>tape</item>
        <item>clay</item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item>The fan that is mounted on the air cart can hurt fingers
          when it is powered by the battery, so watch out for your
          fingers!  </item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Adding a propeller to a cart">
        <steps>
          <step>Use scissors to trim the ends of the plastic propeller
            (approximately 1cm) so that the ends of the propeller
            won&apos;t hit the ground. <ext-image name="02_pr"/>
          </step>
          <step>Press the propeller onto the shaft of the motor. The
            white dab of paint should face toward the motor.  <ext-image name="01a_pr"/>
          </step>
          <step>Turn the propeller with your finger. Looking at its
            shape, can you tell which way the air will blow? How do you
            know? How would you explain it to another person? Record
            your explanation in Notes on your handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Now test your prediction. Choose the direction the
            propeller should turn to make the air blow away from the
            cart. While holding onto your cart, connect the battery
            wires to the motor. You can use the springiness of the wires
            to hold them lightly in place.  <ext-image name="03a_motorWire"/>
            <p>If the propeller doesn&apos;t blow away from the cart,
              reverse the wires.  </p>
            <ext-image name="03a_motorWire"/>
          </step>
          <step>Was your prediction correct? </step>
          <step>While still holding onto your cart, carefully hold your
            other hand in front of and behind the propeller while it is
            on. Do you feel air moving in both locations or only in one?
            Is this the same as what you predicted? In Notes on your
            handheld computer, record the difference you observe and why
            you think it&apos;s that way.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Measuring the motion of a propeller-driven cart">
        <steps>
          <step>Connect the SmartWheel to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the SmartWheel. </step>
          <step>Find a smooth surface, such as a tabletop or a linoleum
            floor, where the air cart will roll smoothly and easily.
            Drape the connecting wire loosely from above the cart so
            that it doesn&apos;t pull the cart one way or the other. If
            you run the cart a long way, one person will need to walk
            along with it, keeping the wire floppy.  <ext-image name="07_pr"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software and observe the position versus time
            graph. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the
            software. </step>
          <step>Start the propeller, holding on to the cart. Let the
            cart go and let it run for as far as you have space. Be sure
            to keep the wire floppy, so that it doesn&apos;t pull or
            push on the cart.  </step>
          <step>What is the shape of the position graph? Is it a
            straight line? Why do you think it&apos;s this shape? What
            do you think it would look like if your cart could keep
            going farther? Explain your reasoning in Notes on your
            handheld computer.</step>
          <step>Try several times until you get a really good graph,
            then save your data to the handheld computer.</step>
          <step>Change the software to show a velocity versus time
            graph. Refer to Technical Hints on how to switch from
            position to velocity graphs. How is this different from the
            position graph? Is the velocity constant? How do you know?
            What do you think it would look like if your cart could keep
            going farther? Explain your reasoning in Notes on your
            handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Adding a friction sled to a propeller-driven cart">
        <steps>
          <step>Reverse the direction of the propeller and the motor so
            that it blows toward the cart. To do this, place the white
            dab of paint facing away from the motor, and reverse the red
            and black leads.   <ext-image name="01b_pr"/>
          </step>
          <step>Build a sled to drag behind the cart. Fold up one end of
            a file card. Make a loop of thread about 20cm long and tape
            one end of it to the file card.  <ext-image name="08_pr"/>
          </step>
          <step>Hook the loop over the bumper. Use clay to add weight to
            the sled.<ext-image name="09_pr"/>
          </step>
          <step>Connect the SmartWheel to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the SmartWheel.  </step>
          <step>Start the software to measure velocity. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to use the software. Make the
            following measurements one after another with the graph
            running. You will then have all of your data on one graph,
            and you can analyze it.  <steps>
              <step>With no weight on the sled, give the cart a gentle
                push so that it rolls to a stop after about 2m.  </step>
              <step>Start the motor and let the cart go for about 2m.</step>
              <step>Put some clay on the sled and hook it onto the
                bumper. Give the cart a push so that it rolls to a stop
                after about 2m.  </step>
              <step>With the clay still on the sled, start the motor and
                let the cart go for about 2m.</step>
              <step>Approximately double the amount of clay on the sled,
                but not so much that the cart won&apos;t move! Give the
                cart a push so that it rolls to a stop after about 2m.</step>
              <step>With the amount of clay still doubled, start the
                motor and let the cart go for about 2m.  </step>
            </steps>
          </step>
          <step>Save the data to your handheld computer.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Connecting the Force probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the Force Probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Calibrating the Force probe </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Connecting the SmartWheel </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the SmartWheel </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Opening saved data in the CC Lab Book software</title>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step>How does a propeller create a force that pushes on a cart?</step>
	  <step>Would a propeller work in outer space, where there&apos;s
          no air? If not, how could you make something move in outer
          space? </step>
	  <step>Look at your position versus time and velocity versus time
          graphs in Trial II. Explain the differences between the
          position graph and the velocity graph. How are they different
          from graphs where the cart is moving at a constant velocity?  </step>
	  <step>Look at your velocity versus time graph in Trial III. For
          each case, describe the graph and what you think is causing it
          to have that shape.   <steps>
	      <step>no friction, push cart  </step>
	      <step>no friction, propeller  </step>
	      <step>some friction, push cart</step>
	      <step>some friction, propeller</step>
	      <step>more friction, push cart</step>
	      <step>more friction, propeller</step>
	    </steps>
        </step>
	  <step>Do you think the graphs are evidence that friction exerts
          a force like the propeller, but in the opposite direction?  </step>
	  <step>The rate of change of velocity is the slope of the
          velocity versus time graph. Do your graphs give evidence that
          this slope is proportional to the net force on the cart? Does
          this confirm Newton&apos;s Second Law?  </step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>Can you add enough clay to the sled so that the propeller
          makes it reach a maximum velocity and then level off? What do
          the position and velocity graphs look like? This is called
          &quot;terminal velocity&quot;. In what other situations is
          there a terminal velocity? </item>
        <item>Try placing a different designs of wind shields or sails
          on your cart to affect its motion. </item>
        <item>Add clay to the sled until it just won &apos;t move. What
          &apos;s the force on the cart at this moment?</item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
    <investigation name="Collision_I">
      <title>Collision I</title>
      <summary>Investigate what happens during a collision of a cart
        with a wall </summary>
      <question>What happens when two objects collide? </question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image name="wallCollision"/>In this activity you will
        investigate what happens during a collision of a cart with a wall.</intro>
      <think>Collisions happen so fast that it&apos;s hard to see what
        was going on during the event. You just see the results of a
        smashed car or a home run or a sore hand. Sometimes you want big
        forces, as with a baseball bat or a karate chop, and sometimes
        you want to decrease the forces, as with a safety helmet.  <p>In
          this activity you will use the Force probe to actually measure
          what happens during a collision. How big are the forces? How
          long do they last? What features of the colliding objects make
          the forces bigger or smaller? In your group, explain how you
          would increase or decrease the forces during a collision.
          Write or draw in Notes on your handheld computer your ideas
          about how to do this. </p>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <item>CC SmartWheel probe</item>
        <item>CC Force probe</item>
        <item>handheld computer</item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software</item>
        <item>long rubber band or several cut rubber bands and joined
          together (so when they are cut and joined it has a length of
          1/2m)  </item>
        <item>constructed air cart (see Investigation: Air Cart)</item>
        <item>books or (optional) a ring stand</item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item>Be careful with stretched rubber bands. They can hurt if
          you let them go and they hit someone!  </item>
        <item>The fan that is mounted on the air cart can hurt fingers
          when it is powered by the battery, so watch out for your
          fingers!  </item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Weighing the cart with the Force probe">
        <steps>
          <step>The Force probe can be used to measure the force of the
            Earth&apos;s gravity on masses. In other words, the Force
            probe can be used to measure the weight of masses. Connect
            the Force probe to your handheld computer. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to connect the cables.   </step>
          <step>Start the software. Refer to Technical Hints to see how
            to use the software.</step>
          <step>Hold the Force probe so that you can hang things from
            the smaller eye bolt at the end of the arm. Calibrate the
            force probe to zero in this position. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to calibrate the Force probe.  <ext-image name="01a_c1"/>
          </step>
          <step>Try weighing something light, such as a paper clip
            hooked to a pen. Expand the force scale so that you can see
            the change in weight. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to
            use the software. What is the smallest weight that you can
            measure?   </step>
          <step>Weigh something heavy, like a book. Note that the units
            are in newtons, not kilograms. What is the difference?
            Explain your reasoning in Notes on your handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Use a paper clip to make a hook so that you can hang the
            cart from the Force probe. It can be hooked to the bumper,
            around the propeller, or through the cardboard. <ext-image name="01b_c1"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start recording with the software for force. Hang the
            cart from the Force probe for 10 seconds. Remove it and
            check that the force goes back to zero. Stop recording data.</step>
          <step>Pick an average value for the weight of the cart and
            write it down in Notes on your handheld computer. How steady
            was your reading? How much did it vary and why?</step>
          <step>If you hang the cart with a rubber band and weigh it,
            will it be the same? Try it.</step>
          <step>What variations do you get? Can you get a steady
            reading? Explain your reasoning in Notes on your handheld
            computer.  <ext-image name="01c_c1"/>
          </step>
          <step>Calculate the mass, in kilograms, of your cart.<p>The
              conversion is mass (kg) = weight (newtons) / 9.8  </p>
          </step>
          <step>Compare this mass to the masses of the other carts.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Colliding a cart with a wall">
        <steps>
          <step>Place the Force probe on its side wedged in a pile of
            books so that it is at the same height as the bumper of your
            cart. It could also be clamped to a ring stand. Have someone
            hold the Force probe down firmly during the experiment.
            Unscrew and set aside the larger eye bolt if it&apos;s in
            the way.  <ext-image name="05a_cartPush"/>
          </step>
          <step>Make sure the motor and propeller are set for pushing
            the cart. The white dot on the propeller should be toward
            the motor.  <ext-image name="01a_pr"/>
          </step>
          <step>Connect the Force probe to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the cables. </step>
          <step>Set up the Force probe in fast mode (at least 400 times
            per second). Refer to Technical Hints to see how to adjust
            the rate of collection.   </step>
          <step>Calibrate the force probe to zero in this position.
            Refer to Technical Hints to see how to calibrate the Force
            probe.  </step>
          <step>Line up the cart bumper with the Force probe, then roll
            the cart back about 50cm. Mark the distance so that you can
            start the cart in the same place every time.   <ext-image name="02_c1"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start the propeller motor.</step>
          <step>Start recording the force, then let the cart go. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to use the software. Make sure
            it bumps directly into the small eye bolt. Observe the
            behavior of the acrobat during the collision.  </step>
          <step>Stop recording immediately after a good collision and
            save your data to the handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Examine the graph. You will need to expand the time
            scale to see what the force looks like during the collision,
            since it happens in such a short time. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Answer the following in Notes on your handheld computer:  <steps>
              <step>What is the shape of the graph? </step>
              <step>How long did the collision take?  </step>
              <step>What was the maximum force?  </step>
              <step>What did the acrobat do during the collision?</step>
            </steps>
          </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Adding a bungee cord">
        <steps>
          <step>This time you will try a &quot;reverse&quot; collision.
            You will measure the force on a bungee cord attached to the
            air cart when it stretches and bounces back. Connect the
            Force probe to your handheld computer. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to connect the cables. </step>
          <step>Place the Force probe on its side wedged in a pile of
            books so that it is at the same height as the bumper of your
            cart. It could also be clamped to a ring stand. Have someone
            hold the Force probe down firmly during the experiment.
            Unscrew and set aside the larger eye bolt if it&apos;s in
            the way.  <ext-image name="05a_cartPush"/>
          </step>
          <step>Set up the Force probe in fast mode (at least 400 times
            per second). Refer to Technical Hints to see how to adjust
            the rate of collection.   </step>
          <step>Cut a long rubber band to make a bungee cord. Attach one
            end to the Force probe and the other end to the cart. Use
            several rubber bands if needed so that the cord is about
            1/2m long.  <ext-image name="03_c1"/>
          </step>
          <step>Line up the cart with the Force probe, with the rubber
            band lying loosely between them. Hook things together with
            paper clips.  <ext-image name="04_c1"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start recording the force. Refer to Technical Hints to
            see how to use the software. Give the cart a push so that it
            stretches the bungee cord and then bounces back. Catch it
            before it hits the Force probe. Stop recording. Observe the
            behavior of the acrobat.  </step>
          <step>Try this several times, and after a good bounce save
            your data to the handheld computer.</step>
          <step>Examine the graph. You will need to expand the time
            scale to see what the force looks like during the collision,
            since it happens in such a short time. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Answer the following in Notes on your handheld computer:  <steps>
              <step>What is the shape of the plot?</step>
              <step>How long did the collision take? </step>
              <step>What was the maximum force? </step>
              <step>What did the acrobat do during the collision?</step>
            </steps>
          </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Connecting the Force probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the Force Probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Calibrating the Force probe </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Opening saved data in the CC Lab Book software</title>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step>What comparisons can you make between the bumper event and
          the rubber band event? How long did each collision take? What
          was the shape of the graph? What was the maximum force?</step>
	  <step>What is the relationship between the behavior of the
          acrobat and the shape and size of the force graph?  </step>
	  <step>Why do you think the forces were different in the two cases?</step>
	  <step>If you were riding on the cart, which collision would you
          prefer, a collision with a wall or a collision using a bungee
          cord? Why?  </step>
	  <step>How could you decrease the maximum force when the cart
          hits the Force probe? Explain why your idea would work. </step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>Use the SmartWheel to investigate the change in velocity
          during a collision. Compare the wall collision with the bungee
          bounce. How is the change in velocity related to the maximum
          force?  </item>
        <item>Investigate collisions of the cart with the Force probe,
          putting varying masses on the cart.</item>
        <item>Investigate the collisions of the cart with the Force
          probe, changing the distance the cart accelerates before it
          hits. </item>
        <item>Investigate other collision conditions, such as, placing a
          lump of clay as an additional bumper, stiffer or more elastic
          rubber bands, or holding the Force probe more loosely so it
          can &quot;give&quot; a bit in the collision.   </item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
    <investigation name="Collision_II">
      <title>Collision II</title>
      <summary>Investigate what happens during a collision between two
        carts </summary>
      <question>When two objects hit, is the force on one the same as
        the force on the other? </question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image name="2cartCollision"/>In this activity you will
        investigate what happens during a collision between two carts.  </intro>
      <think>Suppose a heavy ball and a light ball bounce off of each
        other. Does each one experience the same force? Do they each
        bounce off with the same velocity they started with? If they
        change, which one changes more, the heavy or the light one?
        Explain your reasoning in Notes on your handheld computer.
          <p>In your group, predict and explain what happens when two
          objects with different masses, like a heavy and a light ball,
          collide. What happens when a heavy truck and a small car
          collide? Is the force on each one the same? What is the
          resulting motion of each object? Write or draw in Notes on
          your handheld computer your ideas about what might explain
          your predictions.  </p>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <item>CC SmartWheel probe</item>
        <item>CC Force probe</item>
        <item>handheld computer</item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software</item>
        <item>2 - long rubber bands (so they have a length of about 30cm
          when cut)  </item>
        <item>constructed air carts (see Investigation: Air Cart)</item>
        <item>hot-melt (or cold-melt) glue gun and glue sticks</item>
        <item>paper clip</item>
        <item>pencil or pen</item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item>Be careful with stretched rubber bands. They can hurt if
          you let them go and they hit someone!  </item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Action and reaction">
        <steps>
          <step>Cut two rubber bands and tie them together to make a
            bungee cord about 30 cm long.  </step>
          <step>Attach one end of the bungee to one Force probe, and the
            other end to the other Force probe. Use the small eye bolt
            to attach the rubber bands.   <ext-image name="01a_c2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Connect the Force probe to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the cables.   </step>
          <step>Start the software for the Force probe. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to use the software.   </step>
          <step>Calibrate the force probe to zero. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to calibrate the Force probe.</step>
          <step>Each team member will pull on one of the Force probes,
            much like a tug-of-war. When do you think the two force
            graphs will be the same, and when will they be different?
            Record your prediction in Notes on the handheld computer.   </step>
          <step>Start recording. Vary the amount of pulling, who pulls
            first, and who doesn&apos;t move.</step>
          <step>Save your data to the handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Compare the graphs from the two force probes. What can
            you conclude? Was your prediction correct? Record your
            thoughts in Notes on your handheld computer.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Forces on colliding carts">
        <steps>
          <step>Screw one Force probe to each cart, so that the eye bolt
            points forward. You will need to remove the bumper and the
            acrobat to do this. </step>
          <step>Set the Force probe on the cart, resting on the flat
            plate that has two threaded holes in it. Mark the two holes
            on the cardboard with a pen or pencil.   <ext-image name="02a_c2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Punch two holes in the cardboard with your pen or
            pencil. Enlarge them from both sides so that a screw will
            just fit through.  <ext-image name="02b_c2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Put the two screws through the cardboard from the
            underside, and screw them into the Force probe plate.
            Tighten them until the heads squeeze the cardboard a little
            bit. A paper clip will work as a screwdriver.  <ext-image name="02c_c2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Screw the larger eye bolt and set it aside. Glue the
            bumper on the smaller eye bolt.  <ext-image name="02d_c2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Weigh both carts by hanging them from the small eye
            bolt. Calibrate the force probe to zero. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to calibrate the Force probe.  <ext-image name="03a_c2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Make the carts equal in mass by adding some clay to one
            of them if needed. </step>
          <step>Predict what the force graphs will look like if you roll
            the two carts toward each other at about the same velocity.
            What if you roll one cart toward the other which is not
            moving? Record your predictions in Notes on the handheld
            computer.  </step>
          <step>Each team should start the software for the Force probe.
            Set the force to fast mode (at least 400 times per second).
            Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the software. </step>
          <step>With the carts horizontal, calibrate the Force probe to
            zero. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to calibrate the
            Force probe.  <ext-image name="04a_c2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start recording. Push the carts toward each other at
            about the same velocity, and let them bounce back.  </step>
          <step>Try this again several times. When you get a good run,
            save your data to the handheld.   </step>
          <step>Look at the force graphs for both teams. Were they the
            same for both carts? How long did the collision take? What
            was the maximum force? Record your observations in Notes on
            your handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Velocities of colliding carts">
        <steps>
          <step>Each team should connect the SmartWheel to their
            handheld computer. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to
            connect the SmartWheel.  </step>
          <step>Predict what the velocity graphs will look like if one
            cart is stationary and you roll the other cart against it.
            What will be the velocity for each cart before and after the
            collision? What will the velocity graph do just at the
            moment of collision? Record your predictions in Notes on the
            handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Start the software to record a velocity versus time
            graph. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the
            software.  </step>
          <step>Start recording. Push one cart toward the other and let
            them bounce. Be sure the bumpers are lined up.<ext-image name="04b_c2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Try this again several times. When you get a good run,
            save your data to the handheld.   </step>
          <step>Look at the velocity graphs for both teams. Were they
            what you predicted? How much did each cart &apos;s velocity
            change? How did the initial velocity of one cart compare
            with the final velocity of the other? How long did the
            collision take? Record your thoughts in Notes on your
            handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Connecting the Force probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the Force Probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Calibrating the Force probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Connecting cables from the SmartWheel to the handheld computer</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using CC Lab Book software for the SmartWheel</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Opening saved data in the CC Lab Book software</title>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step>Trials I and II are examples of Newton &apos;s famous
          assertion that &quot;for every action, there is an equal and
          opposite reaction.&quot; Does it seem to be true in both
          cases? Is the result surprising? </step>
	  <step>If you were pushing on each other with Force probes
          instead of pulling, would they still read the same?&quot;  </step>
	  <step>If one of the Force probes were attached to a wall and you
          were pulling on the other one, would they read the same force?   </step>
	  <step>If a light cart hit a heavy cart at rest, what would you
          say now about the force on each one and their speeds after the
          collision?  </step>
	  <step>Newton&apos;s Second Law asserts that a force is needed to
          change the velocity of an object. The greater the force, the
          more quickly the velocity changes. Do your trials support this
          theory?  </step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>Try other collisions: one cart moving and the other
          standing still; both moving in the same direction, one fast
          and one slow; both moving toward each other, one fast and one
          slow. In each case, make a prediction about the final
          velocities and then compare the results to your prediction.  </item>
        <item>Try collisions between carts of different masses. First
          record the force on each. Are the forces the same? Then record
          the velocity of each. How did the change in forces and
          velocities after the collisions for carts of different masses
          compare to the forces and velocities after the collisions for
          carts of the same mass?  </item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
  </unit>
  <unit name="Energy">
    <title>Transfer of Energy</title>
    <investigation name="Heat_Flow">
      <title>Heat Flow</title>
      <summary>Investigate how to alter heat flow </summary>
      <question>What happens when two objects at different temperatures
        are left in contact with each other?  </question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image name="bathtub"/>In this activity you will investigate
        how to alter heat flow.</intro>
      <think>We are constantly dealing with things at different
        temperatures. Sometimes we want the heat to flow faster
        (cooking) and sometimes we want to prevent its flow (sleeping
        bags). In your group, discuss other situations when you would
        want to alter heat flow. Write on your handheld computer these
        situations and explain how the energy flow changes over time.
          <p>Sometimes we prefer uniform temperatures (a non-drafty
          room) and sometimes we prefer contrast (hot syrup on ice
          cream). Can you think of other times when you want uniform or
          non-uniform temperatures? Which condition (uniform or
          non-uniform) is easier to keep for the longest period of time?
          Describe these situations in Notes on your handheld computer
          and explain how the energy flow changes over time. </p>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <item>CC Fast Response Temperature probe</item>
        <item>handheld computer  </item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software</item>
        <item>Styrofoam cup</item>
        <item>film canister (to measure water volume)</item>
        <item>small ball of clay (size of a large or shooter marble)</item>
        <item>paper towel (to dry off clay)</item>
        <item>water at two temperatures (warm tap water and ice water)</item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item>No specific safety features needed for this activity.</item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Mixing the bath water just right">
        <steps>
          <step>When you mix water at two temperatures (one is too hot
            and the other too cold) to make a bath that&apos;s just
            right for bathing, how much of each is needed? Set up the
            Temperature probe with your handheld. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to set up the Temperature probe. The
            sensitive part is just the very tip, where two wires are
            welded together.   <ext-image name="01_hf"/>
          </step>
          <step>What will happen when you touch the end of the probe?
            What happens when you put the probe in water? Record your
            thoughts in Notes on your handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>For heat to flow from one thing to another, they need
            have different temperatures. In this trial you need to have
            two samples of water at different temperatures. You can do
            this by selecting two of the following:  <steps>
              <step>water cooled with ice</step>
              <step>cold tap water</step>
              <step>room temperature water</step>
              <step>warm tap water</step>
            </steps>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software and observe the temperature versus
            time graph as you test your two choices of water. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to use the software.</step>
          <step>Clear the graph and start again. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Make the following measurements one after another with
            the graph running. You will then have all of your data on
            one graph, and you can analyze it. Before mixing the two
            samples of water together, predict the final temperature in
            Notes on your handheld computer. </step>
          <step>Restart the graph and test the temperature of each
            sample of water. Be sure the two samples are at least 10
            degrees Celsius different from each other.  </step>
          <step>Fill the film canister with one of the samples of water
            and pour it into the styrofoam cup. Quickly place the
            Temperature probe in the stryofoam cup. Fill the canister
            with the second sample and slowly add it to the Styrofoam
            cup. Watch the graph.  </step>
          <step>Stop when you think the temperature has come to a
            relatively stable temperature (equilibrium). Save your data
            to the handheld.  <ext-image name="02_hf"/>
          </step>
          <step>How many seconds did it take? How good was your
            prediction? Would this be a good temperature for your bath
            water? If not, what could you do to change the final
            temperature of the mixture? Record your reasoning in Notes
            on your handheld computer.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Reaching equilibrium in temperature">
        <steps>
          <step>Make a small ball of clay, about the size of a large
            (shooter) marble.<ext-image name="03_hf"/>
          </step>
          <step>Set up the Temperature probe with your handheld. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how set up the Temperature probe.
            The sensitive part is just the very tip, where two wires are
            welded together.  </step>
          <step>Start the temperature graph and run through this series
            of measurements so that you get all of your data on one
            graph. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the
            software.  </step>
          <step>Measure the air temperature.</step>
          <step>Use water from a non-room temperature source. It should
            be at least 10 degrees Celsius different from room
            temperature. Place two film canisters of the water into the
            styrofoam cup so that the clay will be fully immersed.
            Measure the water temperature with the Temperature probe.
              <ext-image name="04_hf2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Stick the probe into the center of the clay ball while
            the probe is still running.  </step>
          <step>Is it about room temperature? If not, why not? Record
            your thoughts in Notes on your handheld computer.
              <ext-image name="05a_hf"/>
          </step>
          <step>With the probe in the clay ball, immerse it in the
            water. Watch the graph. Run it until you think it has come
            to relatively stable temperature (equilibrium).  <ext-image name="05b_hf"/>
          </step>
          <step>While you&apos;re waiting, predict in Notes on your
            handheld computer what you think the final temperature will
            be. How can you tell when equilibrium has been reached? How
            many seconds did it take?</step>
          <step>Save your data to the handheld.  </step>
          <step>What is the final temperature of the combination of
            water and clay? How many degrees did the clay change? How
            many degrees did the water change? Record your answers in
            Notes on your handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Using insulation to prevent heat flow">
        <steps>
          <step>Set up the Temperature probe with your handheld. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how set up the Temperature probe.
            The sensitive part is just the very tip, where two wires are
            welded together.  </step>
          <step>Start the temperature graph and run through this series
            of measurements so that you obtain all of your data on one
            graph. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the
            software.  </step>
          <step>Measure the air temperature.</step>
          <step>Make a small ball of clay, about the size of a large
            shooter marble. Stick the Temperature probe into the center
            of the clay ball.  </step>
          <step>Place the clay ball and Temperature probe in the
            Stryfoam cup that contains water. Any amount of water will
            do that&apos;s NOT at room temperature. Let it come to a
            relatively stable temperature (equilibrium). It can be
            either colder or warmer than room temperature.  <ext-image name="05c_hf"/>
          </step>
          <step>Design an insulation to keep the clay at this
            temperature. You can use any available materials. Record why
            you think your design is good in Notes on your handheld
            computer. </step>
          <step>Leaving the temperature probe in the clay, pull the clay
            out of the water and quickly dry it off. Quickly wrap the
            clay and temperature probe in your insulation system.
              <ext-image name="06_hf"/>
          </step>
          <step>Monitor the temperature of the clay. How long does it
            take to reach equilibrium? Is that better or worse than you
            thought it would be? Record your observations in Notes on
            your handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Setting up the Temperature probe   </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software</title>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step>While mixing water at two temperatures, did the result
          match your prediction? If they differed, why? Derive a formula
          for the final temperature of the mixed water when you use
          equal amounts of different temperatures of water.  </step>
	  <step>Which exchanged heat faster, the water mixed together or
          the clay in the water? Why?  </step>
	  <step>Describe the shape of the graph of the clay temperature as
          it approaches the temperature of the water. Why do you think
          it has that shape?  </step>
	  <step>Do you think the shape of the clay makes a difference?
          Give examples of shapes besides a ball and how they would
          behave differently.  </step>
	  <step>How did your method of insulation compare to other methods
          used in your group? Explain why the differences occurred.  </step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>Mix two parts of one temperature with one part at another
          temperature. Pedict what the final temperature will be, then
          do it. How good was your prediction this time? Derive a
          formula for the final temperature when mixing two different
          amounts of water (of different temperatures) together?   </item>
        <item>Do you think equal volumes of clay and water have equal
          heat content? Devise an experiment to find out.  </item>
        <item>Devise a way to test different insulation materials and
          how well they prevent heat from flowing from one object to
          another. For example, look at different kinds of hot beverage
          containers and how long they keep things hot.  </item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
    <investigation name="Potential_Kinetic_Energy">
      <title>Potential and Kinetic Energy </title>
      <summary>Examine the movement and energy of a cart as it rolls up
        and down a ramp </summary>
      <question>When you roll a cart up and down a ramp, it changes
        velocity. If the total amount of energy is always the same, how
        does it change form?   </question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image name="cartOnRamp"/>In this activity you will relate
        the movement and energy of a cart as it rolls up and down a
        ramp.  </intro>
      <think>A basketball player going for a lay up is a good example of
        an object in motion. Just as the player is ready to release the
        ball, the player exhibits both gravitational potential energy
        (how high the player jumps) and the kinetic energy of motion
        (how fast the player is going). How do these two energies
        relate?  <p>Think about what happens when you are playing on a
          playground swing. How does the amount of energy change when
          you are near the ground compared to the amount of energy at
          the top of your swing? Use Notes on your handheld computer to
          draw the motion of a swing. Where is the (gravitational)
          potential energy the greatest? Where is the kinetic energy the
          greatest?  </p>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <item>CC SmartWheel probe  </item>
        <item>handheld computer  </item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software</item>
        <item>constructed air cart (see Investigation: Air Cart)</item>
        <item>cardboard ramp (see Investigation: Air Cart)  </item>
        <item>books to prop up ramp</item>
        <item>measuring tape or meter stick</item>
        <item>rubber bands</item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item>Be careful with stretched rubber bands. They can hurt if
          you let them go and they hit someone!  </item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Rolling a cart down a hill">
        <steps>
          <step>Set the ramp with a height of 10cm at the higher end.
            Place the cart on the ramp with the back wheels near the
            top. Mark where the back wheels are so you can repeat the
            experiment several times. <ext-image name="01_pk"/>
          </step>
          <step>Connect the SmartWheel to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the SmartWheel.  </step>
          <step>Start the software to read a velocity versus time graph.
            Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Let the cart roll down the ramp and continue along the
            floor or desk. If you have room, let it coast to a stop.
              <ext-image name="02_pk"/>
          </step>
          <step>Stop the software immediately after a good roll and save
            your data to the handheld computer.   </step>
          <step>What is the greatest velocity of the cart? Where does
            this occur? When the cart is rolling, it has what&apos;s
            called kinetic energy, or energy of motion. Yet when the
            cart started, it had no kinetic energy because it was not
            moving. So where did the energy come from? Explain your
            reasoning in Notes on your handheld computer.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Changing the starting height of the cart">
        <steps>
          <step>Connect the SmartWheel to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the cables.</step>
          <step>Set the ramp with a height of 10cm at the higher end.
            Place the cart on the ramp with the back wheels halfway up
            the ramp. Mark where the back wheels are so you can repeat
            the experiment several times.<ext-image name="03_pk"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software to read a velocity versus time graph.
            Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Let the cart roll down the ramp and continue along the
            floor or desk. If you have room, let it coast to a stop.  </step>
          <step>Stop the software immediately after a good roll and save
            your data to the handheld. </step>
          <step>What is the greatest velocity of the cart? Where does
            this occur? When the cart is rolling, it has what&apos;s
            called kinetic energy, or energy of motion. Yet when the
            cart started, it had no kinetic energy because it was not
            moving. So where did the energy come from? Explain your
            reasoning in Notes on your handheld computer.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Bouncing a cart down and up a hill Bouncing a cart down and up a hill  Bouncing a cart down and up a hill   ">
        <steps>
          <step>Connect the SmartWheel to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to connect the cables.  </step>
          <step>Rubber bands can also store energy by being stretched.
            Attach one or several rubber bands (connected in line) to
            one end of the cart. Attach the other end to a table leg or
            stand so that the cart is held halfway up the ramp and is
            free to move up and down. It&apos;s something like a bungee
            cord but at an angle. You may need some string as well as
            the rubber bands.  <ext-image name="04_pk"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software to read a velocity versus time graph.
            Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the software.</step>
          <step>Raise the cart to the top of the ramp and let it go.</step>
          <step>Stop recording after it bounces up and down the ramp and
            comes to rest. Save your data to the handheld.  </step>
          <step>At what points in the cart&apos;s travels did it have
            the greatest speed? At what points did it have zero speed?
            How can you tell from the graph when the cart was going down
            and when it was going up? Explain your reasoning in Notes on
            your handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Connecting cables from the SmartWheel to the handheld computer</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Opening saved data in the CC Lab Book software</title>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step>In Trials I and II, the cart has two forms of energy. The
          first, gravitational potential energy, is proportional to an
          object&apos;s height above the Earth. The higher an object,
          the more gravitational potential energy it has. When in each
          trial did the cart have the greatest potential energy? Why?   </step>
	  <step>The second form is kinetic energy, also called energy of
          motion. It depends on an object&apos;s velocity. When in each
          trial did the cart have the greatest kinetic energy? Why?  </step>
	  <step>Do you think the cart has as much kinetic energy at the
          bottom of the ramp as it had potential energy at the top of
          the ramp? Why? </step>
	  <step>Energy can also be stored in a stretched rubber band.
          It&apos;s another form of potential energy. If you
          &quot;hang&quot; a cart down a ramp with a rubber band, then
          let it bounce up and down, energy is going from (gravitational
          potential) to (kinetic) to (rubber band potential). Look at
          your data from Trial III. Where on the graph is each kind of
          energy the greatest?   </step>
	  <step>After the cart leaves the ramp, it slows down, losing its
          kinetic energy. Where does the energy go?  </step>
	  <step>We often want to store energy for later use. How many
          examples of this can you list? In each case, what is the form
          of stored energy, and what is the form of useful energy that
          comes from it? Hint: The useful energy might not always be
          kinetic energy; it might be light from a bulb, or heat in a
          room.     </step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>Add weight to the cart. Does that affect its final
          velocity? Do you think a heavier cart has more energy than a
          lighter cart, when they&apos;re going at the same speed? Where
          does the additional energy come from?  </item>
        <item>Calculate the cart&apos;s potential energy (PE) and
          kinetic energy (KE). Here&apos;s how:  <p>PE (joules) =
            mass(kg) * 9.8(m/s*s) * height(m)</p>
          <p>KE (joules) = 0.5 * mass(kg) * velocity(m/s) *
            velocity(m/s) </p>
          <p>Use the Force probe to measure the mass (weight/9.8 (m/s*s)
            of the cart. The height of the cart is the distance up the
            ramp times its slope (height of the ramp/length of the
            ramp).  </p>
        </item>
        <item>How are potential energy and kinetic energy related as the
          cart rolls down the ramp? To find out, place the cart with the
          back wheels at the bottom of the ramp and start recording both
          velocity and position. By hand, roll the cart up to the top of
          the ramp and let it roll back down the ramp. After collecting
          your data, pick five times and mark both them on both the
          velocity and the position graphs. One mark should be at the
          top and one just as the cart reaches the bottom of the ramp.
            <p>Calculate the PE and KE (refer to the above formulas) at
            each of these times. In this case, the height of the cart in
            the formula for PE is equal to the slope of the ramp times
            the position reading. Add the PE and KE together. Does the
            sum remain constant? Should it remain constant?  </p>
        </item>
        <item>Change the data from Trial III to view position instead of
          velocity. How is the graph the same, and how is it different?</item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
    <investigation name="Heating_With_Electricity">
      <title>Heating with Electricity </title>
      <summary>Investigate heating with electrical devices </summary>
      <question>Can electricity be used to heat things? </question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image name="lightningBolt"/>In this activity you will
        investigate heating with electrical devices.</intro>
      <think>Electricity is a form of energy that&apos;s proven to be
        extraordinarily useful. It can be generated in many ways. It can
        be produced in one place and sent elsewhere along wires. It can
        be used to do heavy jobs (e.g., electric trains) and delicate
        ones (e.g., a dentist&apos;s drill) and everything in between.
        It can be transformed into many other forms of energy we find
        useful, such as light, heat, sound, or mechanical motion. What
        other forms of energy can you think of that can be obtained from
        electricity? Make a list in Notes on your handheld computer.
          <ext-image name="01_he"/>
        <p>The Genecon is a little generator with the same basic design
          as the huge generators run by hydroelectric dams, coal-fired
          boilers, or nuclear power plants. In every case, some other
          form of energy (e.g., falling water, burning coal, decaying
          radioactive material) turns the &quot;crank&quot; of a
          generator and creates electrical power. In this case, you
          supply the power. Make a list in Notes on your handheld
          computer of several ways that electric power is generated and
          the source of energy in each case.  </p>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <item>CC Fast Response Temperature probe  </item>
        <item>CC Voltage/Current </item>
        <item>handheld computer</item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software</item>
        <item>handheld generator (Genecon)</item>
        <item>heat cell with insulating cover</item>
        <item>mini light</item>
        <item>battery pack</item>
        <item>2 - new 1.5V AA batteries</item>
        <item>clip leads</item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item>Although the hand-held generator is sturdily constructed,
          excessive speed in rotating the handle can result in stripped gears.</item>
        <item>While lighting the mini light with your Genecon, keep in
          mind that the mini light will become hot to the touch. The
          mini light will also burn out if you crank the Genecon too
          fast.   </item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Cranking with a Genecon">
        <steps>
          <step>Set up the Voltage/Current probe to your handheld
            computer. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to set up the
            Voltage/Current probe.   </step>
          <step>Locate the parts for your small &quot; heat cell&quot;
            which consists of a resistor inside a block of aluminum.
            When you put electrical current through the resistor, it
            converts the electrical energy into heat and heats up the
            block of aluminum. The heat cell is placed in insulation to
            prevent heat loss to the environment.  <ext-image name="02_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Remove the heat cell from its insulation. Attach the two
            leads of the Genecon to wires extending from the heat cell.
            Also connect the voltage leads and the current leads of
            Voltage/Current probe to the heat cell. Don &apos;t put the
            heat cell in the insulation yet.  <ext-image name="03_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software to record power. This measures the
            electrical power, in watts, that you are supplying to the
            heat cell with the Genecon. Refer to Technical Hints to see
            how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Try cranking at a fairly fast speed and observe the
            power on your graph. Can you crank at a steady fast rate?
            Now try to crank at a slower steady rate that produces half
            as much power. Record your observations in Notes on your
            handheld computer.   </step>
          <step>Practice until you can do two rates of cranking, slow
            and fast, where the faster rate produces twice as much power
            as the slower rate. Disconnect the voltage and current
            leads.  </step>
          <step>Connect the Temperature probe to your handheld computer.
            Refer to Technical Hints to connect the Temperature probe.
            The sensitive part is just the very tip, where two wires are
            welded together.  </step>
          <step>Put the tip of the Temperature probe into the small hole
            in one end of the heat cell.  <ext-image name="04a_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Set the heat cell in the insulation and close up the box
            with a rubber band.<ext-image name="04b_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Attach the two Genecon leads to the wires extending from
            the heat cell.  <ext-image name="04c_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software for the Temperature probe. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to use the software. Start
            recording temperature.  </step>
          <step>Observe the temperature graph. After 10 seconds, crank
            the Genecon for 30 seconds at the fast rate. Then crank the
            Genecon for 30 seconds more at the slower rate. Then stop
            cranking and continue recording for another 60 seconds.  </step>
          <step>Stop recording the data.</step>
          <step>Expand the graph so that you can see how much the
            temperature rose while you were cranking, and how much it
            fell after you stopped. Put marks on the starting
            temperature, the temperature after fast cranking, after slow
            cranking, and at the ending temperature. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to use the software.   </step>
          <step>Save your data to the handheld.  </step>
          <step>Record the change in these values between each of your
            marks in Notes on your handheld computer. Was each
            temperature rate over time steady?</step>
          <step>Take the heat cell out of its insulating box, cool it
            with tapwater, and dry it off.  </step>
          <step>The heat cell is made so that it takes exactly 10 joules
            of energy to heat it one degree Celsius. How many joules did
            your 30 seconds of fast cranking produce? What about the 30
            seconds of slow cranking? How many joules did the cell lose
            in 60 seconds as it cooled? Record your answers in Notes on
            your handheld computer.   </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Heating with a battery">
        <steps>
          <step>You may have found that it&apos;s a lot of work to
            generate even a little bit of heat! Now you will compare the
            heating you did with the Genecon to the heating a little
            battery can do. Connect the Temperature probe to your
            handheld computer. Refer to Technical Hints to connect the
            Temperature probe.  </step>
          <step>Locate the parts for your small &quot; heat cell&quot;
            which consists of a resistor inside a block of aluminum.
            When you put electrical current through the resistor, it
            converts the electrical energy into heat and heats up the
            block of aluminum. The heat cell is placed in insulation to
            prevent heat loss to the environment.  <ext-image name="02_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Insert the tip of the Temperature probe into the small
            hole in one end of the heat cell. Put on the insulation
            cover and close the box with a rubber band.  <ext-image name="04a_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Use a 2-AA battery pack, which will supply somewhat less
            than 3 volts, to warm the heat cell. You can use the battery
            pack on the air cart for this. Attach one of the battery
            leads, but not the other, to the heat cell.   <ext-image name="05b_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software for the Temperature probe. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to use the software. </step>
          <step>When the temperature graph reaches exactly 10 seconds,
            connect the second lead of the battery pack to the other end
            of the heat cell.  <ext-image name="05c_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Heat the cell for 60 seconds, then disconnect one
            battery lead. Let the graph run another 60 seconds so that
            you can watch the cooling of the heat cell.  </step>
          <step>Stop recording the data.</step>
          <step>Expand the graph so that you can see how much the
            temperature rose while the battery was attached and how much
            it decreased after you stopped. Refer to Technical Hints to
            see how to use the software. Place marks on the starting
            temperature, the maximum temperature, and the ending
            temperature.  </step>
          <step>Save the data to your handheld computer.</step>
          <step>Record the change in these values between each of your
            marks in Notes on your handheld computer. Was each
            temperature rate over time steady?  </step>
          <step>Take the heat cell out, cool it with tapwater, and dry
            it off.</step>
          <step>The heat cell is made so that it takes exactly 10 joules
            of energy to heat it one degree Celsius. How many joules of
            heating did the battery produce in 60 seconds? How many
            joules did the cell lose in 60 seconds? Record your answers
            in Notes on your handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Heating with a light bulb">
        <steps>
          <step>Let&apos;s find out how a mini light bulb compares to a
            heat cell as an electrical heating device. Connect the
            Temperature probe to your handheld computer. Refer to
            Technical Hints to connect the Temperature probe.   </step>
          <step>Divide the student research teams into two groups. Half
            the teams will surround the mini light with clear tape, and
            the other half will surround it with aluminum foil.
              <ext-image name="06a_he"/>
            <steps>
              <step>Tape teams: Hold the tip of the Temperature probe
                against the mini light with a short piece of clear tape
                that goes right around the bulb.<ext-image name="06b_he"/>
              </step>
              <step>Foil teams: Wrap the mini light with a small piece
                of aluminum foil that goes all the way around it. Hold
                the foil in place with a short piece of clear tape.
                Slide the tip of the Temperature probe in between the
                bulb and the aluminum foil.  </step>
            </steps>
          </step>
          <step>Attach one lead of the battery to the mini light, but
            not the other.<ext-image name="06c_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software to record temperature. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to use the software.</step>
          <step>Attach the second battery lead and light up the mini
            light. <ext-image name="06d_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Monitor the temperature plot. Let it run for 30 seconds,
            then disconnect the second lead and let it run for another
            30 seconds. Stop recording.   </step>
          <step>Stop recording the data.  </step>
          <step>Expand the graph so that you can see how much the
            temperature rose while the battery was attached and how much
            it decreased after you stopped. Refer to Technical Hints to
            see how to use the software. Place marks on the starting
            temperature, the maximum temperature, and the ending
            temperature.  </step>
          <step>Save the data to your handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Record the change in these values between each of your
            marks in Notes on your handheld computer.   </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Setting up the Voltage/Current probe </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the Voltage/Current
            probe  </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Setting up the Temperature probe </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the Temperature probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Opening saved data in the CC Lab Book software</title>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step>Discuss the shape of the temperature graph when you
          supplied electrical energy to the heat cell with the Genecon.
          Does it start to heat right away? What does the slope of the
          line tell you? Is it the same for fast and slow cranking?  </step>
	  <step>Compare the rate of heating by the Genecon and the
          batteries. Which heats faster? How can you tell? Are you
          surprised by the amount of cranking it takes to equal what a
          small battery can do?  </step>
	  <step>Is the amount of cooling significant over the period of 60 seconds?</step>
	  <step>Is the shape of the graph for cooling the same as the
          shape for heating? How long do you think it would take for the
          heat cell to cool down to the starting temperature?  </step>
	  <step>Do you think the energy in the battery could properly be
          called &quot;potential&quot; energy? What form do you think it
          is in?  </step>
	  <step>Why did the light bulb heat up so much more rapidly than
          the heat cell?  </step>
	  <step>Compare the tape teams&apos; data with the foil
          teams&apos; data. Did the bulb heat up faster with the clear
          tape or the aluminum foil? Explain how you think the light
          bulb becomes hot and what difference the covering makes.   </step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>Heat the cell, out of its box, until it reaches about 45
          degrees Celsius. Monitor how fast the heat cell cools down.
          Try the same thing with the heat cell in the insulation block
          and with other insulation systems of your own invention.  </item>
        <item>As you heat the cell with the battery, monitor the
          electrical energy input with the Voltage/Current probe as well
          as the temperature with the FastResponseTemperture probe. Then
          compare the electrical energy that is supplied by the battery
          with the heat energy that is measured in the heat cell. Do you
          think they should be the same? The electrical energy is
          displayed directly on the energy graph. The heat energy is:
            <p>Energy in joules = 10 x (temperature change in degrees
            Celsius)  </p>
        </item>
        <item>As you heat the cell with the battery, monitor the voltage
          of the battery. It should drop slowly. What do you think is
          happening? Where is the battery energy coming from? Do you
          think the battery could heat the cell forever?  </item>
        <item>Put the heat cell in other things, like water or clay, and
          heat them. Explore the idea of heat capacity. How much heat
          energy is needed to heat up different materials?  </item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
    <investigation name="Single_Transformations">
      <title>Forms of Energy: Single Transformations </title>
      <summary>Investigate the benefits of changing one form of energy
        into another form of energy </summary>
      <question>Can all forms of energy be transformed from one form to
        another? </question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image name="singleNRG"/>In this activity you will
        investigate the benefits of changing one form of energy into
        another form of energy.  </intro>
      <think>Energy comes in many forms - electrical, mechanical,
        chemical, light, nuclear - and it can be stored in many ways -
        batteries, springs, water towers, gasoline, radioactive
        materials. To make use of energy, we often want to change it
        from one form to another, then store it, then transform it again
        and use it later on.  <p>How many kinds of energy can you think
          of that you make use of in and around your house? Where does
          each kind come from? How is it stored before you use it? Is it
          changed from one form to another when you make use of it? What
          do you do with the energy? On your handheld, answer these
          questions for each kind of energy.  </p>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <item>CC Voltage/Current probe  </item>
        <item>CC Light probe</item>
        <item>CC Fast Response Temperature probe</item>
        <item>handheld computer  </item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software  </item>
        <item>handheld generator (Genecon)  </item>
        <item>capacitor (1 Farad)  </item>
        <item>constructed air cart (see Investigation: Air Cart)  wire
          clip leads  </item>
        <item>wire clip leads</item>
        <item>heat cell  </item>
        <item>Fresnel plastic lens (5cm x 8 cm) </item>
        <item>black marker or carbon from a burnt candle wick</item>
        <item>sunlight or incandescent light bulb in a lamp with no shade</item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item>When the Fresnel lens focuses sunlight, it produces a
          concentrated beam of light. Be very careful and never focus
          the beam on yourself or anyone else!  </item>
        <item>Never look directly at the sun. Damage to your eyes will result.</item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Storing electrical energy">
        <steps>
          <step>You already know that electrical energy can be stored in
            a battery. There is an even more direct way with a
            capacitor. A capacitor stores electrical charges and can
            release them again as electrical current. Attach the Genecon
            and Voltage/Current probe to the capacitor.  <ext-image name="01b_st"/>
          </step>
          <step>Connect the Voltage/Current probe to your handheld
            computer. Refer to Technical Hints to connect the
            Voltage/Current probe. </step>
          <step>Start the software to record energy. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Crank until you have charged the capacitor. How can you
            tell that it&apos;s fully charged? Hint: Does the amount of
            cranking effort change as the capacitor &quot;fills
            up&quot;?  </step>
          <step>Quickly disconnect one lead of the Genecon as shown,
            leaving the Voltage/Current probe attached. Wait for about
            20 seconds.  <ext-image name="01c_st"/>
          </step>
          <step>Re-attach the capacitor to the Genecon without cranking
            it. What happens? What simple energy transformation has
            taken place?   </step>
          <step>Stop recording data and save to the handheld computer. </step>
          <step>Look at the graph. How did the energy change over the
            course of this experiment? Record your thoughts in Notes on
            your handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Using stored electrical energy">
        <steps>
          <step>Charge up the capacitor with the Genecon and quickly
            disconnect it. <ext-image name="02a_st2"/>
          </step>
          <step>Connect the charged-up capacitor to power your air cart.
            Coil up the extra wire so that it doesn&apos;t rub against
            the wheels. How far can you make it go?  <ext-image name="03_st"/>
          </step>
          <step>Another possible way to use the energy from the
            capacitor is to warm up the heat cell. Place the tip of the
            Temperature probe in the small hole in one end of the heat
            cell.  <ext-image name="04a_he"/>
          </step>
          <step>Close the heat cell in its insulating box by wrapping it
            with a rubber band and connecting the two clip leads to the
            metal wires that are sticking out.  <ext-image name="04b_st"/>
          </step>
          <step>Connect the Temperature probe to your handheld computer.
            Refer to Technical Hints to connect the Temperature probe.  </step>
          <step>Start the software for the Temperature probe. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Charge up the capacitor again with the Genecon and
            quickly disconnect it.</step>
          <step>Connect the capacitor to the heat cell with two clip
            leads and observe the temperature versus time graph.
              <ext-image name="04c_st"/>
          </step>
          <step>Expand the graph until you can read the temperature
            change. Refer to Technical Hints to see how to use the
            software. Continue testing until you get a good temperature
            graph.   </step>
          <step>Save your data to the handheld computer. </step>
          <step>What can you say about the shape of the temperature
            graph? How long does it take for the energy from the
            capacitor to get transferred into the heat cell? Record your
            thoughts in Notes on your handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Calculate how much heat energy (in joules) you obtained
            from the capacitor. The heat cell contains 10 joules for
            each degree of temperature rise. Record your calculations in
            Notes on your handheld computer.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Heating with sunlight">
        <steps>
          <step>Set up the heat cell with the Temperature probe
            attached, but not in its insulating cover. Mark one face of
            the cell black with a marker or carbon from a burnt candle
            wick to increase the absorption of energy.  <ext-image name="05a_st"/>
          </step>
          <step>Connect the Temperature probe to your handheld computer.
            Refer to Technical Hints to connect the Temperature probe.  </step>
          <step>Start the software for the Temperature probe. Refer to
            Technical Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Try focusing sunlight on the heat cell with the Fresnel
            lens. If there&apos;s no sunlight, try focusing light from
            an incandescent light bulb.<ext-image name="05b_st"/>
          </step>
          <step>Monitor the temperature with the Temperature probe. Do
            not heat the cell above 50 degrees Celsius. The aluminum
            could be too hot to touch safely.  </step>
          <step>Save your data to the handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>How fast did the temperature rise? How many square
            centimeters of sunlight does the Fresnel lens collect? How
            does this compare to what a battery or a capacitor will do?
            Record your thoughts in Notes on your handheld computer.</step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Setting up the Voltage/Current probe </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the Voltage/Current probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Setting up the Temperature probe   </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the Temperature
            probe  </title>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step>When you charged the capacitor with the Genecon, then ran
          the Genecon with the capacitor, do you think you obtained as
          much mechanical energy out of the capacitor as you put in it?
          How could you find out? If you didn&apos;t, where did the
          energy go?</step>
	  <step>Capacitors, with their ability to store electrical energy
          and release it very fast, have many uses. A familiar one is
          the flash on a camera. A very small amount of energy is
          released so fast that it makes a bright, but brief, light.
          This is just what a camera needs! But when you want a slow,
          steady supply of energy, as with the air cart motor, a
          capacitor is not the best source of energy. A battery is much
          better. Think of other situations that use batteries and
          capacitors for electrical energy storage.  </step>
	  <step>The Fresnel lens concentrates light from a larger area to
          a smaller area, by bending the light that comes through it.
          This is called refraction. How much do you think the Fresnel
          lens magnified the amount of sunlight reaching the heat cell
          compared to just letting it sit out in the Sun without the
          lens? Compare the area of the Fresnel lens to the area of the
          focused light on the heat cell.  </step>
	  <step>How many devices can you think of that use lenses to focus light?</step>
	  <step>How do you think sunlight is converted into heat? Do you
          think it matters if the heat cell is black instead of plain
          aluminum? Can heat be converted back into light? If so, list
          some examples of this type of conversion.  </step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>Hook several capacitors in parallel and series, using clip
          leads. Charge them with the Genecon for both cases. See if
          either method works better than a single capacitor for both
          running the cart and warming the heat cell.   </item>
        <item>How much brighter is the sun than a incandescent light
          bulb? Measure how fast the heat cell will be heated by
          sunlight compared to light from a bulb.   </item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
    <investigation name="Multiple_Transformations">
      <title>Forms of Energy: Multiple Transformations </title>
      <summary>Investigate how energy can be transformed through several
        steps to obtain a useful form </summary>
      <question>What energy transformations are used in everyday
        devices? </question>
      <intro>
        <ext-image name="multipleNRG"/>In this activity you investigate
        energy being transformed through several steps to obtain a
        useful form.  </intro>
      <think>We use many devices that transform energy from one form to
        another. Sometimes a whole chain of transformations takes place.
        They often do it so smoothly that we don&apos;t even realize
        what&apos;s happening. Each step usually involves some loss of
        useful energy. An automobile engine, for instance, is only 30
        per cent efficient. That is, only 30 percent of the available
        energy in gasoline is available to move the car.   <p>Think of
          some examples where energy is transformed several times before
          it is used. In your handheld Notes, list each of the forms of
          energy in the chain, and what you think the efficiency is for
          each step. Where do you think the wasted energy goes?  </p>
      </think>
      <materials>
        <item>CC Voltage/Current probe  </item>
        <item>CC Light probe</item>
        <item>handheld computer  </item>
        <item>CC Lab Book software</item>
        <item>solar cell</item>
        <item>sunlight  </item>
        <item>clip leads  </item>
        <item>capacitor (1 Farad) </item>
        <item>mini light</item>
        <item>black film canister </item>
        <item>aluminum foil</item>
        <item>handheld generator (Genecon)  </item>
        <item>pulley wheel and plastic bushing</item>
        <item>string  </item>
        <item>50g mass</item>
        <item>paper clip  </item>
        <item>clay  </item>
      </materials>
      <safety>
        <item>Never look directly at the sun. Damage to your eyes will result.</item>
        <item>Although the hand-held generator is sturdily constructed,
          excessive speed in rotating the handle can result in stripped
          gears.  </item>
        <item>While lighting the mini light with your Genecon, keep in
          mind that the mini light will become hot to the touch.   </item>
      </safety>
      <trial title="Electricity from the sun">
        <steps>
          <step>The solar cell changes sunlight directly into electrical
            energy, which can in turn be used for something else. It is
            not very efficient, but the source of energy is free!
            Connect the Voltage/Current probe to your handheld computer.
            Refer to Technical Hints to connect the Voltage/Current
            probe.   </step>
          <step>Start the software to read voltage. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Hook the solar cell to the voltage probe. Try it under
            different light conditions, such as a light bulb, direct
            sunlight, indirect light from the sky. Stop the software and
            save your data.  <ext-image name="01_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>The maximum voltage is about 2V of the solar cell. Can
            you get it to read this high? Record your observations in
            Notes on your handheld.  </step>
          <step>Team up with another group and connect two solar cells
            in parallel, using the clip leads.  <ext-image name="02a_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Mount them on a cart at an angle so that they face
            toward bright sunlight. Clip the leads to the motor.
              <ext-image name="02_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Is there enough power to drive the air cart? What are
            the energy transformations happening when the sunlight hits
            the solar cell connected to the motor on your cart? How
            efficient do you think each step is? Record your thoughts in
            Notes on your handheld computer.   </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Cranking up the lights">
        <steps>
          <step>Attach the Genecon to a mini light. Crank it, but not
            too fast. If excessive cranking takes place, the light will
            burn out!  <ext-image name="05_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Does the amount of light vary according to how hard you
            crank? Record your observations in Notes on your handheld.  </step>
          <step>Connect the Light probe to your handheld computer. Refer
            to Technical Hints to connect the Light probe.   </step>
          <step>Start the software to read light intensity (lux). Refer
            to Technical Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Measure the light level from light bulbs, direct
            sunlight, and light from the sky. Stop recording, but
            don&apos;t clear the data.</step>
          <step>Place the light bulb in a black film canister along with
            the Light probe. Make sure the Light probe faces the light
            bulb. Hold the Light probe and the mini light in place with
            pieces of clay.   <ext-image name="06a_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Cover the opening with aluminum foil to block as much
            outside light as you can.  <ext-image name="06b_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Restart the software to read light. Gradually increase
            the rate of cranking the Genecon. Do not crank too fast, or
            the light will burn out! See if you can establish a
            relationship between how fast you crank and how much light
            is produced. Can you crank so slowly that no light is
            produced?  </step>
          <step>Save the data to your handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>What are the energy transformations happening here? What
            is the efficiency of each one? Do you think the mini light
            is producing only light energy? Record your answers in Notes
            on your handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <trial title="Remote lifting">
        <steps>
          <step>Team up with another group so that you can monitor two
            Genecons on one handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Connect the Voltage/Current probe to your handheld
            computer. Refer to Technical Hints to connect the
            Voltage/Current probe. </step>
          <step>Connect the Voltage/Current probe leads to the Genecon
            leads as shown in the diagram.  <ext-image name="07_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Start the software to read energy. Refer to Technical
            Hints to see how to use the software.  </step>
          <step>Use one Genecon to drive the other, or each try to
            oppose the other. Watch the energy graph. Does it correspond
            to what you are doing with the Genecons? What are the energy
            transformations happening here? Stop recording.  <ext-image name="08a_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Now attach a pulley to one of the Genecons. Leave the
            wires hooked up. Remove one handle. The pulley comes with a
            piece of plastic tubing (bushing). Fit the tubing on the
            Genecon shaft and slide the pulley tightly over the shaft.
              <ext-image name="08c_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Cut about 2m of thread or string. Tie one end through
            the hole in the side of the pulley.<ext-image name="08d_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Wind up the string onto the pulley. Attach a hanging
            weight. You can use a 50g mass from your kit or a heavier
            one of your own. A paper clip works as a hook. It has a mass
            of about 0.3g.  <ext-image name="09a_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Hold the Genecon with its shaft horizontal and the
            string hanging down from the pulley. Its leads should still
            be hooked to the other Genecon, with the Voltage/Current
            leads in place.  </step>
          <step>Restart the software to read energy.<ext-image name="09b_mt"/>
          </step>
          <step>Crank the other Genecon to lift the weight. Can you also
            lower the weight? If the weight is heavy enough, will it
            fall by itself? Try different things, like raising and
            lowering slowly and quickly. Record the order in which you
            did things so that you can relate them to your graph in
            Notes on your handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>Save your data to your handheld computer.  </step>
          <step>What series of energy transformations is happening here?
            What do you think the efficiency of this system is? Record
            your thoughts in Notes on your handheld computer.  </step>
        </steps>
      </trial>
      <hints>
        <hint>
          <title>Setting up the Voltage/Current probe   </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the Voltage/Current
            probe  </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Setting up the Light probe </title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Using the CC Lab Book software for the Light probe</title>
        </hint>
        <hint>
          <title>Drawing in the CC Lab Book software</title>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <analysis>
	<steps>
	  <step>You built a solar car in Trial I! What other features
          would it need to be a practical vehicle?  </step>
	  <step>Open the data from Trials II. Compare all of the different
          light levels you measured. What was the maximum level? What
          was the minimum level?   </step>
	  <step>You were asked to rate the efficiency of each energy
          transformation. Low efficiency means that useful energy is
          lost. Where does the lost energy go, in the case of the
          Genecon, the solar cell, and the light bulb?   </step>
	  <step>Open the data from Trial III. Compare the energy graph
          with your list of what you were doing with the two Genecons
          and the attached mass. What does the graph tell you about
          energy transfer from one Genecon to the other?  </step>
	  <step>Design an energy &quot;Rube Goldberg&quot; machine. This
          type of machine is a wacky series of devices that change
          energy through various forms and ends up serving a purpose.
          Make a drawing of your Rube Goldberg on your handheld
          computer. Refer to Technical Hints to see draw in the
          software. Please no live animals!  </step>
	</steps>
      </analysis>
      <further>
        <item>Measure the efficiency of the Genecon. Here are three ways:</item>
        <item>Build your own energy &quot;Rube Goldberg&quot; using the
          equipment in your kit or anything else you can find!  </item>
      </further>
    </investigation>
  </unit>
</project>
